<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The excellency of moral vertue, from the serious exhortation of St. Paul to the practice of it in several discourses upon Phil. 4. 8. : to which is added, A discourse of sincerity, from John i. 47 / by Henry Hallywell ...</title>
            <author>Hallywell, Henry, d. 1703?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18059</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13044785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13044785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 740:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The excellency of moral vertue, from the serious exhortation of St. Paul to the practice of it in several discourses upon Phil. 4. 8. : to which is added, A discourse of sincerity, from John i. 47 / by Henry Hallywell ...</title>
                  <author>Hallywell, Henry, d. 1703?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 175 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Adamson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John I, 47 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Sincerity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:96884:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>Geo. Royſe, <hi>R. R. in Chriſto Patri ac Domino Domino</hi> Johanni <hi>Archiep.</hi> Cantuar. <hi>a Sacris Domeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 23d, 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96884:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EXCELLENCY OF Moral Vertue, FROM THE Serious Exhortation of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Practice of it.</p>
            <p>In ſeveral Diſcourſes upon <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A <hi>Diſcourſe of Sincerity,</hi> FROM <hi>JOHN</hi> i. 47.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY HALLYWELL,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Cowfold,</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iames Adamſon,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96884:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96884:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reverend Father in God, <hi>JOHN,</hi> by the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Lord Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of all <hi>England</hi> and Metropolitan, and one of their Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy-Council, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO accept of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſes as a Teſtimony of my Humble Thankfulneſs for your Grace's Favours towards
<pb facs="tcp:96884:3"/>
me. The Subſtance of them was lately delivered to a ſmall Country Auditory, into whoſe Minds I endeavoured to inſtill a Generous Senſe of Virtue, being Convinced not only of the Great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of ſuch Monitory Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a Degenerate Age, but fully perſuaded, that if Men Neglect the Sincere Practice of Virtue, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation of their Minds in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the faultleſs Image of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus will never effectually be carried on. I moſt Humbly Beg your Grace's Pardon for their Imperfections, hoping your Grace will not be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:96884:3"/>
at the Meanneſs of an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering which proceeds only from a Deſire of doing Good. And to Aſſure your Grace of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs of my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions herein, I have add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as an Appendix I judged not unſuitable to the foregoing Diſcourſes, one likewiſe of Sincerity, in which your Grace will ſee the high E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and Value I have of that Lovely Qualification.</p>
            <p>Now that God would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Grace in Health and Proſperity for the Good and Benefit of this Church and Nation, and after you
<pb facs="tcp:96884:4"/>
have finiſhed your Courſe, that your Grace may receive a never fading Crown of Glory when the chief Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd ſhall appear, is the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Grace's moſt Humble, and moſt Affectionate, Servant,</hi> Henry Hallywell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96884:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Phil. 4.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Finally Brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any Virtue, and if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THE true life and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Religion conſiſts not in dry and barren Speculation, but in Practice: And that we may the better know what is the matter of our Practice, the Apoſtle here
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96884:5"/>
inſtances in divers Moral Duties which frequently occur in the life of Man; and indeed ſeems to reſolve all Religion into the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hearty Regulation of the Life and Actions according to the Rules and Meaſures of Virtue.</p>
               <p>And becauſe Morality by ſome hath been too much ſlighted and undervalued, and a Moral Man looked upon but as a more refined Reprobate or Caſt-away, I ſhall endeavour to make good this in the firſt place,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the ſincere Practice of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Virtue is the Ground work and Foundation of that Life by which we muſt be ſaved:</hi> or, <hi>That the main and ſubſtantial part of Reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion conſiſts in the Practice of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Virtue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For to be a Chriſtian is to be all this that the Apoſtle menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to be true in our Words and Promiſes, to be honeſt in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96884:5"/>
walking anſwerably to the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Natures, to be juſt in our dealings one with another, to be pure in our Bodies and Souls, and to practiſe ſuch things as are lovely and of good report amongſt the beſt and wiſeſt Men.</p>
               <p>And if there were any Pagans that ever attained to this high and excellent pitch, they muſt be reckoned amongſt thoſe that were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> fitly diſpoſed for the Kingdom of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 9.62. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ranked and ſet in order for Eternal Life. And whoever thinks himſelf to be a Chriſtian without the due obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of theſe and ſuch like Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which flow from true and right Reaſon, he has the name indeed, but wants the thing it ſelf, and does but cheat and deceive himſelf, and will hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter feel the ill effects of his delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96884:6"/>
when he comes into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World.</p>
               <p>By Morality then I underſtand all theſe Virtues the Apoſtle men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and whatever elſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to true and right Reaſon, and tends to the improving and bettering the Life of Man.</p>
               <p>I do not ſay that the Practice of theſe Virtues alone will ſave a Man, becauſe the Goſpel is ſet at ſomething a higher Pitch, and requires ſuch a Nature as cannot be attained barely by theſe: But this I ſay, that all theſe Virtues are the foundation of our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and without the ſincere Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of theſe we ſhall never be ſaved. They are as neceſſary to Salvation, as the caſting of Corn into the Ground is to the future Harveſt. And he that is not right in the practice of theſe, let him otherwiſe never ſo much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud himſelf, is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96884:6"/>
a true Chriſtian, that he is but a diſſembling Hypocrite both in the ſight of God and Man.</p>
               <p>Now that the main of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion conſiſts in the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Moral-Virtue will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear;</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſeems to ſet this as the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end and perfection of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>Micah 6.8. <hi>What doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</hi> that is, God requires nothing more or greater in compariſon of theſe: for otherwiſe there were other things which God required as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate parts of his Worſhip, and a Prevarication in which had doubtleſs been a very great ſin; but he required the Practice of theſe Virtues chiefly, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96884:7"/>
of themſelves, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that the doing theſe things is more grateful to him than a Thouſand Sacrifices. And Chriſt himſelf approved of what the Scribe ſaid, <hi>Mark</hi> 12.33. That <hi>to love the Lord with all our heart, with all our underſtanding, and with all our Soul, and with all our ſtrength, and to love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as our ſelves, is more than all Burnt-Offerings and Sacrifices.</hi> For though God had commanded the Daily Sacrifice to be offered, yet the practice of Moral Virtue was more pleaſing to him, this hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an inward Goodneſs and Lovelineſs in it, which the other had not. Nay, God diſdains and reproaches even the Acts of his own Worſhip, when they are performed by Men of unholy Lives and Converſations, as we read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your Sacrifices
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96884:7"/>
unto me, ſaith the Lord? I am full of the Burnt-Offerings of Rams, and the fat of fed Beaſts, and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light not in the blood of Bullocks, or of Lambs, or of He-goats.</hi> Here is a manifeſt ſlighting even of thoſe very Acts of Worſhip which he himſelf had injoined; and what ſhould be the reaſon that the Lord ſhould abhor his own Offering, and not be pleaſed with what he himſelf had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? We find it expreſſed, <hi>Verſe</hi> 15. <hi>Your hands are full of Blood.</hi> They were guilty of open Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Tranſgreſſions of the Eternal Laws of Nature. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it follows, <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. <hi>Waſh ye, make ye clean; put away the evil of your doings from before my eyes, ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, relieve the Oppreſſed, judg the Fatherleſs, and plead for the Widow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96884:8"/>From hence you ſee that it is clear as the Sun, that God puts a higher eſtimate and value upon the faithful diſcharge of theſe Moral Duties of Religion, than he does upon the immediate Acts of his own Worſhip. And that whatſoever Service is performed to him, it is no further accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than as it ſtands in Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with Acts of Kindneſs, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence, Juſtice, and Equity, towards our Fellow-Creatures. Nay our Saviour himſelf and his Apoſtles, when they would give us a brief Summary or Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of Religion, they always make the practice of Moral-Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to be the main part and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of it. For thus our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord himſelf ſays, that to love God and our Neighbour, are the ſubſtance of the Law and the Prophets. And St. <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.27. that <hi>true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96884:8"/>
before God and the Father is this, To viſit the Fatherleſs and Widows in their Affliction, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, the value that God puts upon Moral-Virtue, is ſo great, that when the Scripture gives a Character of any perſon that is dear and acceptable to God, the deſcription is for the moſt part drawn from inſtances of Morality. In the 31ſt Chapter of <hi>Job,</hi> we find that Holy Man making a profeſſion of his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Integrity, and all the inſtances he gives of it, are but ſo many Acts of Moral-Virtue; yet has he this Commendation given him, <hi>That he was a perfect and upright man, one that feared God, and eſchewed Evil,</hi> Job 1.1. And that which indeared <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> to God, and made him be thought worthy of the Viſit of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96884:9"/>
an Angel firſt, and then of an Apoſtle, was, (as we read, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2.) <hi>That he was a juſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Man, one that feared God with all his Houſe, and gave much Alms to the people; and prayed to God always.</hi> Inſomuch that St. <hi>Peter</hi> makes this general Dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Concluſion from it, <hi>Verſe</hi> 34, 35. <hi>Of a truth, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that God is no reſpecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but in every Nation he that fears him, and worketh righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is accepted with him.</hi> As if the Apoſtle had ſaid, In all times and ages whoever he be, and in whatſoever part of the World, that acknowledges the being of a God, and ſincerely honours him, and lives up as near as he can to the Preſcriptions of right Reaſon, that Almighty Being looks down with a favourable Eye upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96884:9"/>Certain it is, that Chriſtianity it ſelf whoſe ultimate end is the Salvation and Bleſſedneſs of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind hath therefore appeared, (ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Tit.</hi> 2.12.) teaching us, <hi>That denying all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and Worldly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent World.</hi> Which is nothing but the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Morality. And that we may conclude this Argument, when the Apoſtle would give us the Character of a compleat and full grown Chriſtian, he ſays, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. that he is ſuch a one who by reaſon of uſe hath his Senſes exerciſed to diſcern both good and evil. So that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all Religion is made to conſiſt in having a vital relliſh and diſcrimination of good and evil.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96884:10"/>2. By theſe Moral Actions we partake of the Nature of God. The Apoſtle in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. makes the ultimate End and grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Chriſtian Religion, to be our partaking of a Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Now the Nature of God, as it is communicated to us, does not conſiſt in Wiſdom or Power, but in Goodneſs and Truth, in Holyneſs, Juſtice and Equity, in Love, Commiſeration and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. All which are Moral Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies and Perfections, and as we partake more or leſs of them, ſo do we more or leſs reſemble and draw down God into our Souls. The Eternity, Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Omnipotency of God, are no where ſet as our Copies to follow; for theſe are Incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable Properties of his Nature; but in all his Moral-Perfections, we are to imitate and become like unto him. It is by his Holineſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96884:10"/>
and Purity, by his Love and Goodneſs, that God falls down into our Souls, and impregnates them with his Sacred Life, and forms there his own Image and Likeneſs. And we cannot doubt but that which ſo nearly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles God, and is nothing but his own Life and Nature copyed out and implanted in his Creatures, muſt needs be moſt of all valued and reſpected by him; and we are in his Favour as we increaſe in Holyneſs and Purity, in Truth, Goodneſs and Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Now that God accounts theſe Things moſt dear to him, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from that Example he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to us for our Imitation, that is, The Example of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who was God dwelling in our Nature, and in whom that Divine Life, which is the higheſt Perfection of Men and Angels, was moſt clearly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96884:11"/>
and conſpicuouſly diſcovered. And the great Things which have made the Life of Chriſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amplary, and ſet as a Godlike Pattern for us to follow, were</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Superlative Love and Charity; deſigning not ſo much his own Intereſt, as the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal and common Good of all the World. His Kindneſs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions were not circumſcribed to this or that particular ſort of Men, but extended and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to all that were capable of them. He made no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Age or Sex or Parties, but ſcattered his Bounty to all, and filled all Places and all Perſons with Joy and Gladneſs by his Preſence. And whenever he made uſe of that Almighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which reſided in him, it was not to the Harm and Damage, but to the Support and Relief of thoſe he converſed withal.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96884:11"/>2. Again, he made his Life an Examplary Pattern to us in his Humility, and the Reſignation of his Mind to the Divine Will and Pleaſure. For we never find our Saviour ever arrogating any Praiſe or Glory to himſelf, but refers all the Glory of his Actions to God. Inſomuch as (though he knew himſelf to be Innocent and without Sin, yet) he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be called Good, ſaying, <hi>That none was good, ſave one, that is, God.</hi> And whatever his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was, he never murmured or repined at it, but entirely committed himſelf to the wiſe Providence and Diſpoſal of God. Nor did he ever deſire the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling his own Will and Deſires any further, than they might conſiſt with the good Pleaſure of his Heavenly Father.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And then laſtly, Our Lord has given us a clear Example of an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96884:12"/>
unſpotted Purity both of Body and Soul. He converſed with a Wicked and Cenſorious World, with Men that lay at the catch to enſnare him, and yet we do not read they could ever faſten any Sin upon him. And as his Soul was ever kept undefiled and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted from the World, ſo his Body was never polluted by any inordinate Pleaſure or Exceſs; but both Body and Soul remained always pure as the Temple of the Living God. Here now is that Divine Nature that we are called to partake of, and this is the perfect Image and Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the Divinity that we are to be conformed to; and yet theſe are no other than Moral Vertues; and our partaking of the Nature of God is the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of our Souls to theſe and ſuch like Rules of Eternal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96884:12"/>3. The Practice of Moral Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues is ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that without it we can never perform any Chriſtian and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Service unto God. The Ten Commandments muſt firſt be kept before we can arrive to that higher meaſure of Perfection re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us under the Goſpel; and we muſt firſt be good Men before we can be good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and none can be good, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be true and faithful, and juſt and honeſt. For what Sign can that Man give that he deſires to be like to God in Juſtice and Equity, who never omits any occaſion of injuring and defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Neighbour? How can he be ſaid to be a Follower of Jeſus, who went about doing good, that will neither afford Relief to the Bodies or Souls of Men? God is Love, but when Men live in Envy and Hatred and Malice, it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96884:13"/>
were ſtrange they ſhould be like to God. Suppoſe any Perſon ſhould ſay, That he deſires and hopes to inherit the pure State of Angels hereafter; can we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this, when we ſee him at the ſame time purſuing all beaſtly and ſenſual Pleaſures? The Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Moral Vertue is a thing that God has put into our Power, and he requires that we ſhould be faithful to it; becauſe from hence Springs that new Nature which is wrought in us by the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowing Power of the Spirit of God. There is ſuch a near con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection between theſe Moral Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and that Divine Life which Jeſus came to plant in our Souls, that one cannot be without the other; nor can we perform any Service acceptable to God, while we either neglect, or are falſe in the Practice of theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96884:13"/>Theſe are the Arguments which may ſerve to enforce the ſerious Practice of Vertue in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral upon us, and to let us know that the eſteem which God hath of us, is according to our Growth and Progreſs in it. All other Qualifications are of little or no worth in Compariſon of this. And if we are defective here, though we are otherwiſe never ſo gloriouſly accompliſhed, it will do us no good.</p>
               <p>We may now briefly conſider the Incouragements the Apoſtle gives to the faithful Diſcharge of theſe Virtues in general. They are theſe two, expreſs'd, <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That theſe things are not new nor ſtrange; the Apoſtle deſires nothing but what they had learnt, and heard, and ſeen in him. If they feared the Truth of what he ſaid, they ſhould look
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96884:14"/>
on him, and ſee if his Life and Actions were not conformable to his Doctrin. Examples are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Encouragements to a Holy Life; and Chriſtians ought not to walk every Man by himſelf, but imitate and ſtir up and follow one another in the ſame Courſe of Holineſs. That as they offer up the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Petitions and Prayers for themſelves and all Mankind, ſo they ſhould all ſtrive together and incourage one another in the ſame way of Virtue; that ſo at laſt they may all come to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and felicity of Jeſus who is gone before them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He tells them the God of Peace ſhould be with them in ſo doing. The higheſt Motive and Incentive to the Practice of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Virtue that can be thought of. Though all the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96884:14"/>
World be in a Storm and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion about us, yet ſo long as we are Holy and Good, that God who Creates an Everlaſting Peace for Righteous Men, ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with us. And where he is preſent there is an Eternal Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs and Calm: God will never forſake his own Life and Nature; and Holineſs being the very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, he cannot but love and regard it wherever he finds it in any perſon. Though Earthly Parents may forget their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yet God cannot be unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of thoſe that are Good, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Holy. He can never withdraw himſelf from them, but will continually viſit them with his Powerful Love. He gives them that Peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this Life, that the World cannot give, and brings them at laſt to that Land of Peace and Bleſſedneſs where there is no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96884:15"/>
Diſturbance or Alteration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Whatſoever things are true.</head>
               <p>The Goſpel being given to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the Manners, and reform the Lives of Mankind, and to bring into uſe thoſe Virtues which began to grow out of faſhion through the general Wickedneſs and Corruption of the World; the Apoſtle begins with Truth; <hi>Whatſoever things are true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Truth is to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it refers purely to the Underſtanding.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it relates to Practice.</p>
               <p>Firſt in Opinions, and in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to our belief of any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96884:15"/>
that is propounded to us; and thus 'tis oppoſed to Error or Falſhood and Hereſie. So that when the Apoſtle injoins us to follow thoſe things that are true, he would have us entertain no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctrins but ſuch as are purely Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Now although a good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an that believes the Scriptures, and ſincerely endeavours to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them aright, and to lead his Life according to them, may be well aſſured, that God will keep him from all Errors that are deſtructive of his Salvation; yet becauſe Error is ſo various, and that there be too many who act the Devil's part, and make it their buſineſs to delude Harmleſs and Innocent Perſons; it will not be amiſs to lay down ſome few Rules, whereby we may diſcern true Doctrins from falſe, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our ſelves in a good meaſure
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96884:16"/>
from being impoſed upon. For the Scripture being a Book that is not all of the ſame Nature, nor written by one Man in the ſame Method and Style, but is filled in ſome places with Advices and Counſels to that which is beſt; ſometimes with Precepts and Commands; and in other places with dark and obſcure Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; and laſtly, with the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Parts of true Reaſon and Knowledg, though often deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſomewhat a Myſterious way: Theſe things being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it is impoſſible that all Men ſhould have the ſame Thoughts and Apprehenſions, and conceive of all places in the Scripture after the ſame way and manner. Hence it comes to paſs that ſome Men through weakneſs and careleſneſs, and others out of deſign, broach many Errors and Falſhoods, and ſpread them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96884:16"/>Therefore if there may be ſome plain Rules ſet down, which may ſerve as a Mark to guide us in a doubtful and dangerous way, it cannot but be gratefully recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by every one that loves Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity and Truth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Therefore, whatever Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin is repugnant and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Goodneſs, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power of God, it is to be rejected as an Error. For the Goodneſs, Wiſdom and Power of God are ſo manifeſt in all things, and in all places, that as no Man can miſs of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Being of his Creator, ſo it cannot be a Truth that ſeeks to diminiſh and obſcure thoſe Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Attributes of the Deity which ſo evidently appear throughout all the Tracts of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe ſpace.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96884:17"/>Thus then, when we look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Frame of the World, nay, but into the Fabrick of our own Nature, and ſee with what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Art and Contrivance things are made, and how each Part is ſubſervient and conſpires to one great End and Purpoſe, that is, for the good of the whole; this very Conſideration, That things are made and framed for Ends and Deſigns, will lead us to the knowledg of a Conſcious and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Nature, which is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than an infinitely Good, and Wiſe, and Powerful God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any one ſhould go about to perſwade us, that either the Beautiful Frame of this viſible World, or the Admirable Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Humane Bodies in which is lodged ſo much Art and Skill, had no other Original but blind Chance and Fortune, and aroſe from the Fortuitous Coalitions of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96884:17"/>
Atoms; we cannot but look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it at firſt ſight as an Error and Deluſion, becauſe it derogates and takes away from that Infinite Power and Wiſdom, which we behold in the making even of the leaſt thing in the World.</p>
               <p>Again, if any Perſon ſhould tell us, that God made the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of Mankind on purpoſe to Damn them, without any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their Sin and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations: It is impoſſible (keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves to this Rule) that ever we ſhould believe ſuch a Doctrin, becauſe it is ſo contrary to his Goodneſs and Love, which as it brought all things into Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for no other end, but that they might be Happy, ſo it will never deſtroy or turn any thing out of that Happy State, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it's own demerit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96884:18"/>To inſtance once more; If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man ſhall Teach, That the Commands of God are impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be performed, and that though he invite all Men, yet he denies ſufficient Grace to the greateſt part of them, whereby they may be inabled to Obey him, and be Extricated out of their Miſerable Condition:</p>
               <p>By this Rule we ought to look upon ſuch a Doctrin as a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Falſhood: Becauſe it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that an Infinitely Wiſe and Good God cannot command and injoin Impoſſibilities; nor exact and require Men's Obedience to his Laws, without furniſhing them with a ſufficient Power whereby to do them. And to do otherwiſe, would ſo little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Name of Juſtice and Equity, that it would be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Tyranny and unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Self-will.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96884:18"/>Hence now it follows, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe Inſtances, but in any other Doctrins whatever; if they any way leſſen the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Wiſdom, or Power of God; if they diſparage all or any of theſe Attributes, ſuch Doctrins can never be true. For Truth is always the ſame and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and is ever found agreeable with the Nature of God, who is the Fountain of all Truth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If any thing be taught that is contrary to the undoubted Principles of found Reaſon, or the clear Evidence of Senſe, it is to be looked upon as Falſe.</p>
               <p>Becauſe Reaſon is that Lamp or Candle of the Lord which he has lighted and ſet up in the Soul of Man, whereby it is able to make a difference, and diſcern between Truth and Falſhood. And our Senſes are another infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96884:19"/>
means of Communicating the true Knowledg of things to us, when they are ſound and not vitiated, and their Objects duly and conveniently Circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated. Now as our Eyes and Ears were given us to diſcern Objects of Sight and Hearing; ſo are our Reaſons to diſcern thoſe things that belong to Reaſon. And as no Man, (but ſuch a one as is Crazed in his Intellectuals,) will diſtruſt his Eyes or Ears when their Objects are duly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; ſo neither will he diſtruſt his Reaſon when it Acts accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe common and ſelf-evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Notions upon which all Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is founded. And that this may yet be more manifeſt, it is to be Conſidered, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man is not indifferent to Truth or Falſhood; that is, no Man can believe what he pleaſes whether right or wrong. It is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96884:19"/>
not in the Power of any to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that to be True, which he knows to be Falſe, becauſe there is ſuch an ungratefulneſs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeableneſs between Falſhood and the Rational Nature of Man; and to believe a Falſhood, were to offer Violence to our Rational Faculties.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, becauſe it is not in the Power of Man to believe or disbelieve at his Pleaſure, his Underſtanding being limited and bound up by thoſe Eternal Rules of Truth and Falſhood, it is clear, that Right Reaſon muſt be the meaſure of Truth and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and conſequently that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin muſt be Falſe that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Reaſon. To give ſome light to this in a particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: Our Adverſaries of the Romiſh Church ſay, that Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation is True, that is, that the Conſecrated Wafer, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96884:20"/>
every Crum of it, is the whole and entire Body of Chriſt that hung upon the Croſs: But ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Rule, it is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Falſe, becauſe it is contrary to the Reaſon and Senſe of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. It is contrary to Reaſon, becauſe Chriſt's Natural Body cannot be in Heaven, and at the ſame time, without any continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of it ſelf, be in a Thouſand diſtant Places upon Earth. And it is contrary to the Evidence of Senſe, becauſe Three of our Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>viz.</hi> our Taſting, Touching, and Seeing, inform us, that it is ſtill Bread. And if our Faculties may deceive us in their proper Objects, it is impoſſible we ſhould ever arrive to the certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of any Thing, but muſt be Condemn'd to an Eternal Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm. But that our Senſes are true Judges when they are right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Circumſtantiated, appears from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96884:20"/>
all the Miracles which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our wrought, which are only ſo many Appeals to the Evidence of Senſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whatever Doctrin or Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion there be in Religion that does not drive at Holineſs of Life, nor deſign the Perfection of Men's Souls, it is to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all one as if it were Falſe.</p>
               <p>For all the Myſteries and Truths of the Chriſtian Religion are ſuch, as ſome way or other ſerve to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in us a true Fear and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God, and tend to the making us better. Their Deſign is to communicate ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God and of his Works to us, as may affect our Hearts, and render us more God-like. Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is the Intent and Purpoſe of the whole Goſpel, and whatever does not in ſome meaſure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and advance a Pious and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96884:21"/>
Religious Life, cannot be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to come from God.</p>
               <p>Thus if a Man ſhall imagine that a bare Naked Faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an inward Change and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation of the Mind is enough to ſave him; or if he ſhall frame to himſelf any Opinion that gives any Liberty, Indulgence, or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, to any Sin: Theſe and ſuch like Fancies are utterly Falſe and to be Abhorred, becauſe they deſtroy the great End of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the inward Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Purity and Sanctity of the Mind and Spirit.</p>
               <p>By theſe Rules we may Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min the Truth of all Doctrins propounded to us, in order to God and to Religion. And this may ſerve as an Explication of Truth as it relates to the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96884:21"/>2. Truth as it relates to Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, is properly Veracity, and is oppoſed to Lying and Deceit. To be plain and true hearted in our Words and Promiſes accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſimplicity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. So that when the Apoſtle bids us mind ſuch things as are true, it is all one with his Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Wherefore putting away Lying, ſpeak every Man the Truth with his Neighbour.</hi> For God being a God of Truth, and not capable of deceiving Men either in his Words or Promiſes, he would have Men to be like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. And this Duty is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary upon theſe Two Accounts;</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the Conformity and Likeneſs it hath to the Nature of God.</p>
               <p>God is repreſented in the Old Teſtament by the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that cannot Lie; and in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96884:22"/>
the New, the Apoſtle Argues from the Immutability of the Nature of God, that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to Lie or to Deceive. For to Lie is a Weakneſs, Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Imperfection of the Mind, which God cannot be ſubject to. No Power or Force can conſtrain him to do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than his Nature wills; and his Counſels and Will being directed by an Infinite Goodneſs and Wiſdom, there cannot be in him any Variableneſs, Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or ſhadow of turning. And he is moſt like unto God who ſtands Confidently and Immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to what is True and Right. For Truth deriving from an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and Almighty Being, is bold, and takes place, when Deceit and Falſhood is put to its Shifts, and runs into holes, hating the light. Therefore the wiſer Heathens uſed to ſay, <hi>That to ſpeak the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96884:22"/>
Truth, and to do Good, were things that made us moſt like to God.</hi> And moſt certain it is, that the more a Man ſwerves and declines from Truth, the further he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from a Participation of the Nature of God. Hence when the Jews would not believe our Saviour, who teſtified that Truth he had received of God, he tells them, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. <hi>They were of their Father the Devil, who was a Lyar, and the Father of it.</hi> He was the firſt Inventer and the firſt Author of Lies in the World: <hi>Therefore,</hi> (ſays Chriſt,) <hi>when he ſpeaketh a Lie, he ſpeaketh of his own.</hi> 'Tis none of God's Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, but an effect which he is the ſole Cauſe and Author and Original of. When that foul Spirit had once disjoined and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated himſelf from God, then he began to Lie and to Deceive, and taught Men to do ſo too;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96884:23"/>
which ſhewed the weakneſs of his Nature, when once it became uncentred and unhinged from that Stable and Unchangeable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who is Truth it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Truth is the Bond and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Civil Society. There is no Commerce or Intercourſe between Men in the World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this. And hence it is that a Liar is baniſhed and excluded from all ſober Society; and the Reaſon is, becauſe he deſtroys that which God and Nature or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained ſhould preſerve and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Correſpondence one with another. Therefore the very For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, that is, the Nature of a Lie includes in it a piece of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and is a real Injury done to another. For Words and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions being only the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Minds one to another, every Man has a right of judging
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96884:23"/>
and underſtanding by theſe what is ſignified to him. Now when a Man tells a Lie, he impoſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Neighbour, and deprives him of his Right, by making him to believe quite contrary to what the things are. Therefore our Bleſſed Saviour tells us, <hi>That for every idle Word that Men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall be accountable,</hi> Mat. 12.36. which is not meant of every impertinent or uſeleſs, but every vain or falſe Word, <hi>i. e.</hi> for every Lie. And there is a great deal of Reaſon for this, becauſe he that Lies to another, not only betrays the Effeminate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Weakneſs of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but is really injurious to his Neighbour, and deſtroys and undermines that which is the common Cement and Bond by which Societies are incorporated together.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:96884:24"/>Wherefore let it be every Man's Care to avoid all Fraud and Diſſimulation in his Words and Actions. For nothing is more unbecoming a Man, much more undecent and odious is it in a Chriſtian, who profeſſes a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that owns the greateſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and openneſs, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and plain-heartedneſs in the World. Our Bleſſed Saviour tho' he many times prudently avoided Captious and Enſharing Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet when he was demanded an Account of that for which he came into the World, <hi>i. e.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were the Chriſt, or the true Meſſiah, he owns it, though he knew this very Truth would coſt him his Life. When the Cauſe of God and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience lies at ſtake, then Truth muſt in a particular manner ſhew it ſelf: For to Diſſemble and to be Falſe to this, is to betray the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96884:24"/>
Religion that we profeſs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we find among the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of thoſe that are excluded from the Kingdom of Heaven, are all ſuch as <hi>love and make a Lie, Revel.</hi> 22.15. not only ſuch as make Deceits and Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to betray the Truth, but ſuch as love and delight in ſuch Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Actions. And in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs terms, God Almighty Threatens all Liars, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8. <hi>That they ſhall have their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone.</hi> Becauſe Falſhood is not only contrary to the Nature of God, and ſinks us into a Condition the furtheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from him, but deſtroys the Intereſt of Chriſtianity, which requires in all its Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors the greateſt Truth and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in all their Words and Actions. Chriſt came to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a Fair and Innocent Nature
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96884:25"/>
in the World, which cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with thoſe Blemiſhes and Spots that attend Lying and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. Truth is plain and eaſie, but a Lie is crooked and perverſe, and made up of many windings and turnings. So that he that conſiders the Nature of God who is abſolute Truth, the Intereſt of Religion, and the Good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, will not think ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation as this to be unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but will with all diligence purſue and follow ſuch things <hi>as are true.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Whatſoever things are honeſt.</head>
               <p>Beſides what we have here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of Virtue in general, we may further Note, that theſe and ſuch like are the Moral Furniture of our Souls; they are the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts and Derivations of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96884:25"/>
Nature of God, which however by a long Degeneracy they ſeem to be worn out, and the Traces of them in many to be ſcarce vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; yet there is ſuch a Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Congruity between them and the Nature of our Souls, that they are ready to embrace whenever duly offered to them.</p>
               <p>After having adviſed to things true, the Apoſtle comes next to <hi>whatſoever things are honeſt:</hi> which is not to be taken in a ſtrict ſignification, as Honeſty is a part of Juſtice, (for that St. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions afterwards,) but the word <hi>[honeſt]</hi> here muſt be taken in a larger ſignification, for whatever is becoming. So the Word in the Original imports, <hi>whatever is venerable, grave, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and becoming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For doubtleſs there is ſuch a thing as Natural Decency and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96884:26"/>
                  <hi>Decorum,</hi> which may be rated according to the different Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Qualifications of Men. Thus ſome things may paſs irreprehenſible in a private Perſon, which are unbecoming a Prince. And that which may be allowed in another would yet be unfit for a Miniſter of the Goſpel, who is to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>of good behaviour,</hi> which in <hi>Verſe</hi> 8. is expreſſed by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Grave, i. e.</hi> Adorned with a comely Gravity and Decency in his whole Converſation. So that whatever Degree or Place a Man holds in the World, he ought to Act ſuitably and agreeably to it. Thus Parents and Maſters ought to ſet their Children and Servants an Example of Gravity and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comingneſs. Which though in many things it is to be taken and meaſured from the Uſe and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96884:26"/>
of the Place and Nation wherein they are, yet there are ſome General Rules of becoming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which Nature and Reaſon will furniſh us withal. For <hi>Grave,</hi> and <hi>Venerable,</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming,</hi> being Things of a Moral Nature, it is certain, that there is ſome Rule and Meaſure, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by theſe things are to be known, as well as for any other Vertue. As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. This Gravity and Become<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſs which the Apoſtle adviſes us to follow, requires that we Act in all things ſuitably to the Dignity of our Nature. We are to Conſider, that God hath made us Rational Creatures, and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us with a Power of diſcerning between Moral Good and Evil. Now we having the Laws of Good and Evil, of what is Baſe and Deformed, and what is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96884:27"/>
and Becoming engraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Souls, whenever we Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs theſe Rules, we Act contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Excellency and Dignity of our Nature. Hence was that Precept of the Philoſophers, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verere teipſum, Reverence thy ſelf, i. e.</hi> Take Care that thou Act not below the Dignity and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of thy Nature. For Right Reaſon being that Rule and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure according to which all our Actions are to be formed and ſquared, whenever we ſwerve and deviate from that Rule, we go below and debaſe our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>And this Superiority of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon over all our Animal and Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Paſſions and Inclinations is denoted in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28. where God bids Man <hi>have Dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea, and over the Fowl of the Air, and over every living thing that moveth upon the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96884:27"/>
Earth.</hi> There are many Paſſions and Affections and Senſations which ariſe from the Body, and as they are Innocent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo they are Neceſſary to the Perfection of our Nature. Wherefore Man being made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Image of God, he has likewiſe an Empire and Rule and Dominion given him over all his Bodily Affections and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to moderate and guide them in the leſſer World, as God doth all the parts of the greater throughout the whole Creation. Thus St. <hi>Jude, Verſe</hi> 6, ſpeaking of the Lapſed Angels, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which kept not their firſt Eſtate, the Vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> has it, <hi>Principatum ſuum non ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaverunt;</hi> which is thus expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Simplicius</hi> after the <hi>Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical</hi> manner,<note place="margin">In Epictet. p. <hi>163.</hi>
                  </note> and in terms very little different from the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96884:28"/>
that Archical Power wherein conſiſted their ſimilitude with God, and giving themſelves up to the Conduct of their irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Appetites. Now when the Bruitiſh Life leads us aſtray from the Government of Reaſon, and we caſt away that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Principality and Archical Rule wherewith God hath inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us over all our Corporeal Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Affections, then the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Creation is inverted, and the Beaſt governs the Man; than which nothing can appear more unbecoming and unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to every one that hath any ſpiritual ſenſe and diſcerning in him.</p>
               <p>It was an Evil which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays he ſaw under the Sun, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Servants upon Horſes, and Princes walking as Servants upon the Earth.</hi> The Moral is true in every Wicked Man, in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96884:28"/>
whom Reaſon is dethron'd, and the loweſt of his Appetites and Deſires command and force him to obey them. For any Man therefore by Intemperance, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, and a lawleſs purſuit after ſenſual Pleaſures, to abuſe any Power of his Body, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of his Soul, he does that which is Diſhoneſt and Uncome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in forcing Reaſon from its Seat, and ſetting up his Brutiſh Luſts in its ſtead.</p>
               <p>To be carried out in a fond doating upon the World, and an immoderate love of Senſual Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and to follow them with a mighty eagerneſs and deſire, as if they were the ultimate Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Man, it is to debaſe and diſhonour our Souls. It is an abuſe and a ſlur caſt upon Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, becauſe we make uſe of it to thoſe Purpoſes which God never intended it for. In
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96884:29"/>
like manner, to be over-curious in making Proviſion for the Body, and to beſtow too much time in Decking and Adorning that to the Prejudice and Neglect of the Soul; it is what is unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming and diſhonourable to a Man; becauſe 'tis a preferring our worſer part before our Souls, which are much the Nobler half of us.</p>
               <p>Now as for that Decency which ought to be even in our Apparel, it is to be meaſured by the Cuſtom and Manners of the beſt and wiſeſt Perſons among whom we live; whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this Caſe ought by no means to be ſlighted or underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued: The State likewiſe and Condition of Perſons is to be Conſidered; <hi>They that are Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly Apparalled, and live Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately,</hi> (ſays Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.25.) <hi>are in King's Courts.</hi> In which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96884:29"/>
our Saviour does not condemn the wearing of Rich Apparel, either as a thing undecent or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, but ſeems to intimate, that the Quality and Condition of Perſons is to be obſerved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Gravity and Comelineſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that in all our Actions we conſider the end of our Beings; and that we Act ſuitably and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably to that end. Every thing is ſuch as is the end to which it is determined; and as the end is more or leſs Noble, ſo is the Excellency of a Creature proportionably more or leſs. Now the higheſt and beſt end of Man as a Rational Creature muſt undoubtedly be the Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nature of God; for there is nothing in the World more Noble, nothing more Excellent than this. Wherefore all Comelineſs and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96884:30"/>
                  <hi>Decorum</hi> conſiſting in an apt and due order and conſent, it follows that we then Act the moſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming, when we Act the moſt Agreeably and Conſonantly to the Great and Univerſal End of our Beings. Therefore whatever it be that hinders our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with God, and our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of his Nature, ſo far forth it is Diſhoneſt, Vile and Unſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our Intellectual Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>It was good Advice of the Wiſe <hi>Ben Syrack, Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 7.36. <hi>Remember the end, and thou ſhalt never do amiſs.</hi> For he that Acts agreeably and conformably to the end of his Being, he Acts accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Order which God hath appointed, and therefore cannot be guilty of any thing that is Baſe and Unworthy. Let them ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Conſider this who can qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly and contentedly wallow and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:96884:30"/>
tumble in Senſual Pleaſures; who are never better pleaſed than when with the Serpent they are Creeping upon the Ground, and Licking the Duſt; how infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they deviate and ſwerve from that great End of their Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! Man was made to be united to God, and to Converſe with him, and therefore hath ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Powers in his Soul as are fitted to that Purpoſe. But when our Underſtandings and our Wills, when our Love and our Deſires are taken up with the ſearch and complacency they find in Worldly and Senſual Objects, theſe Faculties and Paſſions of our Souls are miſplaced, which breeds a Diſorder and a Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this is what in it ſelf is diſhoneſt and unbecoming.</p>
               <p>Every Exceſs and Exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of our Paſſions is an Indecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not only as it ſinks a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96884:31"/>
the Dignity of his Nature, by Exalting the Brutiſh Part in him, but as it deſtroys and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the Great End of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is, his Participation of the Divine Nature, which is the moſt Calm, and Uniform, and Sedate thing in the World.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Gravity and Becomingneſs command us to Treat Holy Things and Perſons with that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence that is due and proper to them.</p>
               <p>Virtue is not a thing that is merely acquired, and transfuſed into us from without, but rather an Exſuſcitation and raiſing up of thoſe Intellectual Principles, <hi>Pro re nata,</hi> and according as the Circumſtances of Humane Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons invite, which were Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Engraven and Sealed upon the Soul at her firſt Creation. And amongſt the Reſt, this is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96884:31"/>
one of thoſe Laws or Principles which are Connate and Born with us, <hi>That we ſhould Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence our Superiors;</hi> and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Degrees of their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, ſo our Reverence and Eſteem and Honour are to be paid. Thus God is to be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the higheſt Honour, to be Loved with the greateſt Love, and Served with the moſt Chearful and Sincere Obedience, becauſe he is the moſt Excellent Being, the Fruitful Cauſe and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal from whence all Things both in Heaven and Earth flow and derive themſelves.</p>
               <p>And if it be Judged among all Nations a thing very unbecome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deride and treat our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents with Contempt and Scorn, much more is it when this Abuſe is offered to God himſelf, and paſſes upon Things or Perſons that for his ſake are called Holy.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96884:32"/>
It is one of the Great and Crying Sins of this Age, that Men are grown of ſuch a light and frothy Temper, as to think it the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of their Wit to Laugh at the Notion of a God, to Ridicule the Scriptures, and to Expoſe to Scorn the Sacred Perſon of our Bleſſed Saviour. And he that can do this with the fineſt Fancy, and Cloth the Lewdneſs of his Mind in the Neateſt Dreſs, is Applauded by the reſt of the Herd, and paſſes for a moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Wit; though it be ſuch a kind of Wit as the Devils themſelves are either Aſhamed or Afraid to make uſe of, (for they tremble at the thoughts of God,) but theſe Whifflers who have neither Learning nor good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, are neither Afraid nor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed by their Rude Drolling and Buffooning to Expoſe to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt all that which the wiſeſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96884:32"/>
and beſt Men in the World have always had the greateſt Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for. And how Unbecoming and Uncivil a Thing this is, the Univerſal Senſe of Mankind ſpeaks aloud, and whoever has but a dram of true Wiſdom and Underſtanding left in him, muſt needs Abhor it, as contrary to that Gravity which Nature her ſelf inſtructs Men in.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To Expoſe any Man to Scorn and Contempt for any Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of Body or Mind, is inconſiſtent with the Rules of Gravity and <hi>Decorum.</hi> For as for the Imbecillities and Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Mind, ſince all Mens Souls were Caſt in the ſame Mould, and the diſtinction that is made, proceeding from a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and reſerved Providence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unknown to us, it were very Unbecoming to Expoſe them
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:96884:33"/>
to Scorn for that whoſe Reaſons we are perfectly Ignorant of. A Fool is rather the Object of our Pity and Commiſeration, than of our Contempt and Deriſion. And to Vilifie and Upbraid another for any Defect or Deformity of Body, it is to Upbraid him for that which was no more in his Power to help, than it was in his Power not to be Born. Leaſt of all does it become us to make our ſelves Merry with other Mens Sins, but rather to Mourn and Weep that they are ſo degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and fallen from the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Height of their Creation. And as for their Follies, though they may ſeem to give an Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for Deriſion, yet it is better to imitate the ſad and ſober Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Holy Jeſus, of whom we Read that he ſometimes Wept, but never that he Laught.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:96884:33"/>5. Laſtly, Chriſtian Gravity will Teach us to avoid all Filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Fooliſh Talking and Jeſting, which this Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Are not convenient, i. e.</hi> they are not agreeable to that Gravity and Modeſty that a Chriſtian ought to Obſerve. Out of the Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Heart the Mouth ſpeaketh, and he that either uſes or delights in Obſcene and Filthy Diſcourſe, it is a certain ſign that the Frame and Temper of his Soul is ſtrangely ſunk and bemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Fleſh and Blood. And though <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanity,</hi> which is here rendred <hi>[Jeſting,]</hi> be reckoned by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> as a Virtue that helps to Accompliſh a Man, and thoſe who neither willingly uſe, nor take any pleaſure in Jeſts, are by him termed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ruſtical:</hi> Yet as the one will hardly Merit the Name of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:96884:34"/>
unleſs it be uſed with great Caution and Prudence, ſo the other iſ ſo far from Ruſticity, that it may rather ſeem the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altedneſs and Heroicalneſs of the Mind, that Slights and Underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues theſe little Flirts of Wit as Mean and Trivial. In a Word, We that profeſs Chriſtianity ought to behave our ſelves with that Becomingneſs as that we may neither be Taxed with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perciliouſneſs, Pride, or Scorn, nor yet with a Vain, Light and Frothy Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Whatſoever things are Juſt.</head>
               <p>We have Diſcourſed of the Two Firſt of theſe Virtues men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by St. <hi>Paul;</hi> the next in order is to Conſider of ſuch things as are Juſt. And let no Man look upon the Practice of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:96884:34"/>
theſe Virtues as Mean and Light, and a thing of no Conſequence; for whoever is defective in theſe can never truly pretend to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. For the true Chriſtian Life is made up of ſuch things as theſe are; and he that is not true in his Words and Promiſes, that does not act ſuitably and agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to that Nature God has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in him, and moreover can allow himſelf knowingly to defraud his Neighbour, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver plauſible Covering he may ſhelter himſelf under, yet he can never paſs for a true Chriſtian in the ſight of God or Man. We are too apt to believe that we ſhall be ſaved, though we tranſgreſs theſe Rules of Virtue; and we may go on and deceive our ſelves if we will, but when we come into the other World, we ſhall find the great Enquiry there to be, whether we have Acted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:96884:35"/>
to the Preſcriptions of Virtue or not. Hence it is that the Holy Apoſtle ſo fervently Exhorts us to the Obſervance of all Virtue, and particularly of that which is Juſt.</p>
               <p>God has made Man a Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Creature, and by this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed him from Brutes. Now Right Reaſon is nothing but that Eternal Law which God has En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon every Man's Soul; and from this general Law of Reaſon are derived all Particular Virtues; amongſt which this of Juſtice, which always ſuppoſes ſome Law, to which as to ſome ſtanding Meaſure all its Acts muſt be Reduced and made Conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For Juſt in a large ſenſe is no more than Crongruous and Agreeable: And there muſt be ſomething which of neceſſity muſt be the Rule and Meaſure of this Congruity and Agreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:96884:35"/>
which can be nothing elſe but that Nature of Eternal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that God hath formed in our Souls. Hence it follows, that to do that which is Juſt, is to do that which is Agreeable to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Immutable Reaſon.</p>
               <p>But the Words of the Apoſtle here, ſeem a little more reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confined, and when he ſays, <hi>Whatever things are Juſt,</hi> it is all one as whatſoever things are Righteous. Now Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that reſpects others, and then to be Juſt is to give every Man his due. And that we may know theſe things the better, Chriſt gives us an Excellent Rule (which is indeed the foundation of all Juſtice, and for which the very Heathens Reverenced Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,) <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Whatever you would that Men ſhould do to you, do ye ſo to them.</hi> Into this great Principle all Natural Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:96884:36"/>
and Equity may be reſolved. Which that we may not abuſe by a wrong underſtanding of our Saviour's meaning, (as ſome are too apt to do, thereby to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate, excuſe or ſhift off their Sin) there are Two things to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it was not Chriſt's Mind to Confound the different States and Conditions of Men; as if by this Law Princes were bound to perform all thoſe Duties back again to their Subjects, that their Subjects do to them: Or that Maſters are bound to Obey their Servants, becauſe they would have their Servants Obey them: Or that Parents ſhould Reverence their Children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Children are obliged to Reverence and Honour them. For this would deſtroy all the differences of things, and ſet
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:96884:36"/>
Princes and People, Maſters and Servants, Parents and Children, upon equal terms; which it was never Chriſt's intent to do. But only to conſider how we would be dealt withal, if we were in the place of thoſe we deal with, and to Act accordingly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor did our Saviour intend that this Precept, <hi>[of doing as we would be done by,]</hi> ſhould be enlarged to things Unjuſt, and againſt the Common and Publick Good of Mankind. As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Becauſe Men that Violate the Sanctions of Right and Juſt, and break thoſe Laws that are made for the Common Profit of the World, would willingly be freed from Puniſhment, that therefore we are bound by this Precept of Chriſt to deal ſo with them. For this would be to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all Wickedneſs and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:96884:37"/>
and to open a Door to all the Villanies and Enormous Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Vileſt Wretches can think to commit. This were to give a liberty to Wicked Men to Invade that which is anothers, and to Countenance Rapine and Fraud by Chriſt's Law. Therefore it is certain, that our Saviour who came to diſcountenance all Vice, and to give Men Rules of Holy Living, and teach them Juſtice and Equity, never intended his Words ſhould be underſtood in this Senſe. But his Words are to be reſtrained to whatever is Lawful and Right; that which is agreeable to the Nature of God, who is the higheſt and moſt Impartial Juſtice; a Copy of which he has Tranſcribed and Written in every Man's Soul.</p>
               <p>And ſo the Command ſignifies thus much, That we never do that to another, which if we
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:96884:37"/>
were in that other Man's place, we would clearly and truly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be Injuſtice, and againſt the Laws of Evident and Right Reaſon. To give a plain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this Law; If a Man were brought into great Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Straits and Diſtreſſes, he would willingly be relieved by thoſe that are able to help him; therefore now he muſt do the ſame to others, and be ready to relieve them. If a Man would not be Defrauded or Oppreſſed by another, he is bound by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Command to bear ſuch an Honeſt and Juſt Temper of Mind, as not to Defraud and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and Circumvent and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs any other.</p>
               <p>You ſee now by this what the Apoſtle means by things that are Juſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is to follow that Excellent Precept of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, in which all the Parts of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:96884:38"/>
Juſtice are in a few Words com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, <hi>i. e. To do as we would be done by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now you will better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and peradventure remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this, if I ſhew you in a few particulars what every good Man deſires, and would have done to him; for then you will evidently diſcern, that what you deſire to your ſelves, you ought to do to others.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Every Good Man deſires above all things his own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both in this Life and in the next. And ſince he is ſo willing to have this for himſelf, it is a piece of Chriſtian Juſtice and Charity, that he ſhould ſtand ſo affected to all others. He would not have any Man diſturb the Eaſe and Comfort and Quiet of his Life here; he deſires not to be Pained or Grieved, or to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:96884:38"/>
have his Spirits waſted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with Cares and Miſeries. Now if we would but be as Juſt to others as we are to our ſelves, we ſhould not only deſire but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to help forward, (as far as we are able,) the Happineſs of all Mankind. We ſhould Comfort thoſe that are caſt down, and pour in the Oil of Joy and Gladneſs into the Bones that God has broken; we ſhould never behold any Watry Eyes, but be ready to dry them up; nor find any Aking Heads, but endeavour to Bind and Eaſe them. We ſhould never ſend away any without the real ſigns of our Charity and Compaſſion. If there be any that deſire our Counſel and Advice in weighty and doubtful Affairs; any that are wavering and unſettled in Religion, that ſtand in need of, and want ſome Faithful Guide to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:96884:39"/>
reſolve and ſettle their Fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating Minds: All theſe are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to which this great Law of Juſtice obliges us to afford our beſt Skill and Aſſiſtance; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would deſire the ſame at their Hands, if they were in our Circumſtances, and we in theirs.</p>
               <p>Let thoſe then reflect ſeriouſly upon themſelves, and behold how far they are removed from this great Law of Juſtice and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who take delight in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of others; that are pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in anothers Ruin and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that have an inward Joy and Contentment, (as it were) when they have Defrauded and Over-reached another. And yet their own Hearts teſtifie againſt them, that they would not be ſerved ſo themſelves; they would not willingly receive ſuch Meaſure again. Is there not all
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:96884:39"/>
the Reaſon in the World that Men ſhould abſtain from doing that which they are not willing to receive?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Every Good Man would willingly enjoy ſo much of this Worlds Goods, as may make his paſſage Comfortable while he is Travelling towards the next. And if every Man wiſh ſuch things to himſelf, in Juſtice he ought not to Envy them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; much leſs ought any to hinder or endeavour to fruſtrate the honeſt Induſtry and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of another to ſupport him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the World: And the Reaſon is, becauſe no Man would be Abuſed ſo himſelf. And if Men would always in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their Duty to others ſtrive to ſquare their Actions by this Rule, the World could not be ſo over-run with Deceit and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:96884:40"/>
Treachery. If every one when he is going to hinder the welfare of another, or Oppreſs and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach upon his Neighbour, would but Ask himſelf the Queſtion, Would I be pleaſed to be ſo dealt with by another? Or, if I might have my own Choice, would I not deſire to be otherwiſe uſed by other Men? Why then ſhould I mete that Meaſure which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to receive again? This would be the way to free the World from that great Burden of Cruelty and Oppreſſion that it groans under. There would not be ſo many Complaints of Mens hard Uſage of one another; of their Unmercifulneſs, and thoſe frequent Inſtances of Rapine and Extortion. Moreover every Man does not only wiſh and deſire his own Good, but this deſire is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and accompanied with real Endeavours. What a Man does
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:96884:40"/>
for himſelf, he does it with a real intent to do himſelf good; and with the ſame Meaſure ought all others to be Treated. <hi>Let Love be without Diſſimulation,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 12.9. Every Man loves himſelf ſincerely, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that all others ſhould do ſo too; which by way of Juſtice engages us all to unfeigned Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without Hypocriſie. Thoſe that the Apoſtle mentions in <hi>James</hi> 2.16. that would give good Words to the Poor and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent, and bid them <hi>depart in Peace, and be Warmed and Filled,</hi> but never gave them any thing whereby they ſhould be ſo; they would not have been ſerved ſo themſelves: They would have ſaid, that Good Words could not Fill a Hungry Belly, nor Cloth a Naked Back, nor Warm Chill and Benummed Limbs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is Unjuſt that uſes thoſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:96884:41"/>
very Courſes he Complains a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Every Man deſires that God would Pardon all the Offences done againſt him; and if ſo, then our Saviour's Rule of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice muſt take place in reference to others. For if we deſire that God would remit the Treſpaſſes done againſt him, it were Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in us to Treaſure up the Wrongs of others againſt us in order to a Retaliation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. Nay our Bleſſed Lord is ſo expreſs in this Duty, that he makes it a part of our Prayers to be forgiven no otherwiſe than we forgive others. This would make the World better indeed, if all Men were Convinced they ought to walk thus; and if upon this Conviction they would ſincerely endeavour to manage the Courſe of their Lives accordingly; there
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:96884:41"/>
would not be ſo much Hatred and Malice, and Revenge and Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in the World as there is: But Men's rough and uneven Tempers would be changed and wrought into Mildneſs and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, forgiving one another, as God for Chriſt's ſake has forgiven them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Every Good Man would have God ſupply all his Wants and Neceſſities, and therefore in Juſtice we ought to do the ſame to others. We that muſt Ask even our Daily Bread at the Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Hands of God, muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that there is a piece of Juſtice due to others: Whether it be to ſupply the Bodily Wants and Neceſſities of any one; or whether it be to Comfort a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Spirit, and Cheer up a drooping Soul; or whether it be to defend the Cauſe of ſuch as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:96884:42"/>
are injuriouſly Wronged and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. All theſe are parts of Juſtice that we owe to others, foraſmuch as we would have them deal in that fair manner with us. <hi>With what Meaſure ye mete, it ſhall be Meaſured to you,</hi> ſaid our Saviour, <hi>i. e.</hi> you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but expect that God and Man ſhould deal with you as you deal with others.</p>
               <p>You ſee now by theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Inſtances, (which are all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in that general Precept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned of our Bleſſed Lord,) how Comprehenſive this Virtue of Juſtice is. And I have the rather made choice of them for their plainneſs-ſake, and the general Influence they have upon all the Actions of our Lives, and alſo becauſe Juſtice ſeems to bear a part, and to be interwoven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Frame and Nature of all other Virtues, and from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:96884:42"/>
Conſideration of other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Virtues, the ſeveral Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Juſtice may be taken. For as Juſtice reſpects God, it is <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,</hi> as it relates to Men, it may be termed <hi>Probity;</hi> and becauſe Mercy, and Kindneſs, and Good-Nature, are due to their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Objects, ſo far forth they are comprehended under Juſtice, and involved in that Golden Rule given by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>It remains now that we brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſecute ſuch Inferences as may naturally flow from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Exhortation to ſuch things as are Juſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This Teaches us that Juſt &amp; Right, are not Arbitrarious and Factitious things, and Changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by Will and Pleaſure. They are not things that are merely made ſo by Law, for then it would be in the Power of Men
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:96884:43"/>
to turn the greateſt Villanies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt Conſummate Virtues, and Conſecrate Wickedneſs by the Sanction of a Law. Indeed <hi>Plato</hi> as he is Cited by that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently Learned Perſon Dr. <hi>Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> repreſents the Old Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtick Hypotheſis ſomething after this manner,<note place="margin">Intellectual Syſtem, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>892.</hi>
                  </note> That every Man has an infinite Right to all things, and that whatever his Senſual Appetite deſires, (though it be the Murder of another Perſon,) he has a Right to do it, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is impoſſible that all Men ſhould have Dominion, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man having a Natural Right, or <hi>Jus ad omnia,</hi> it ſo came to paſs, that after Men had been a good while Cutting and Slaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Juſtling againſt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, (the State of Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a State of War againſt all,) they became at length weary hereof, and therefore compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:96884:43"/>
the buſineſs amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they agreed together by Pacts and Covenants, neither to do nor ſuffer Injury, but to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Rules of Equality, and make Laws by Compact, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their Peaceable Cohabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they calling that which was required in thoſe Laws by the Name of Juſt. Here we have the Sum of the Atheiſtick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks, whoſe Foundation is laid (as the forecited Author ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,) in the Villanizing of Humane Nature, as that which has not the leaſt Seeds of Equity and Philanthropy, Charity or Benevolence, but what ariſes from mere Fear, Imbecillity and Indigency. No Care and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for Publick and Common Good, but tends directly to the deſtruction of all Society. For if there be nothing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Juſt, that is, If there be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:96884:44"/>
no ſuch thing as Juſt and Right Naturally and Antecedently to all Will and Power, but that it wholly ariſe and flow from Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Determination, then it will not be Unjuſt for any Man to break and reſcind thoſe very Compacts and Agreements which he himſelf hath made, as oft as he hath Opportunity and Power ſo to do. Which muſt effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy all Society, and leave all Men in a State of War one with another, the Greater and more Powerful, like Brutes, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally preying upon and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Weaker. But that there is ſuch a thing as Juſt and Right by Nature, is pertinently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by that great Poiloſopher Dr. <hi>More,</hi> in his uſeful Treatiſe of <hi>Ethicks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> where upon <hi>Andronicus Rhodius</hi> his Definition of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<q>That it is that by which the Defect and Error of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:96884:44"/>
Law is ſupplied and corrected: He adds, If there be nothing Juſt but by virtue of ſome Written Law, what need is there of Emendation of the Law, ſince the Law it ſelf, be it what it will, makes any thing Juſt? But it is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Equity to Correct the very Law, and to appoint ſuch things upon Emergent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which (if he could have foreſeen them) the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator himſelf would have Conſtituted and Appointed; which yet were very Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, if the Nature of Juſt and Unjuſt depend wholly upon the Arbitrament and Pleaſure of the Legiſlator, and not upon the Nature and Circumſtances of things themſelves.</q>
Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to conceive of Juſt and Right as things Eſſentially inherent in God, who is that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:96884:45"/>
and Living Law from whence all Juſtice and Equity flows. And he has Engraven theſe Principles in Humane Souls; ſo that if there had never been any Poſitive Laws made, yet there would have been ſuch a Nature as Juſt and Right, which was ſo Yeſterday, to Day, and will be for Ever, Eternally In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent upon all Will whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are informed that all Men in the World have a Right to Juſtice, and though they be never ſo Wicked, they ought not to be Injured or Wronged. For Juſt and Right being Eternal and Unchangeable things, that can never alter, or be otherwiſe than they are; the outward Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Men ought to make no alteration in them. Though a Man therefore be never ſo Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:96884:45"/>
he muſt not be Defrauded, or Injured, or Oppreſſed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he has a Right by God's Order and Decree to the things of this World, and conſequently cannot without Injuſtice be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoiled of his Propriety. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Fancy of ſome, who think none but Saints have any true Right to Earthly Poſſeſſions and Enjoyments; whereas cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly their Claim is the leaſt, their Holy Lord himſelf ſaying, <hi>That his Kingdom was not of this World.</hi> Chriſt's Religion doth not Juſtifie an Unrighteous Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though done to a Wicked Man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It Teaches us that there is no Sin ſo Black and Heinous as that of Injuſtice. For as Juſtice in ſome ſenſe comprehends all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Virtues under it; ſo all Sins have ſome tincture of Injuſtice in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:96884:46"/>
them. For there is a Right that is due to God, another to our Neighbour, and a Third to our ſelves; and to violate and break any of theſe is a piece of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. But beſides this, the Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of Injuſtice appears in this, in that it is the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Societies: It is that which is a manifeſt Nuſance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the well Being of the World, and that which turns the Earth into a deſolate Wilderneſs to be Inhabited only by Wild Beaſts. Therefore this Sin being ſo contrary to the Nature of Man as he is a Sociable Creature, and ſo oppoſite to God's Providence and Government of the World, hence it is that there is no Sin ſo ſeverely taken notice of as this of Injuſtice. For the Great Lord and Father of all having Ranked all Beings that are capable of Moral Good and Evil, under their
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:96884:46"/>
diſtinctive Families, and formed them into ſeveral Societies and Corporations, whatever in their reſpective Precincts deviates from the Rules of Juſt and Right, muſt have a more ſevere Inquiry than any other Fault, foraſmuch as it more or leſs tends to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw or ſubverſion of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It Teaches us in all our Actions to follow that which is Juſt. Which if every Man would carefully endeavour to do, the World would ſoon be turned into a perfect Heaven, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come once more the Habitation of Righteouſneſs. And why ſhould not Men endeavour to bring on ſuch a Spirit of Benignity and Righteouſneſs, which may put an end to all Rapine, Cruelty and Oppreſſion? That may take off their Minds from the World,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:96884:47"/>
which is commonly the Cauſe and Root of Injuſtice? He that follows that which is Right and Juſt, will certainly find the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of it. He ſhall have Peace of Conſcience here, and the great Reward of Bleſſedneſs hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Whatſoever things are pure.</head>
               <p>The Apoſtle comes now to urge the following and practiſing ſuch things as are <hi>pure:</hi> The Old Tranſlation renders it <hi>Sancta,</hi> as ſuppoſing it to have been Read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Whatſoever things are holy.</hi> Now the Univerſal Chriſtian or Divine Life being expreſſed fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by this general Term of <hi>[Holineſs,]</hi> of which <hi>Purity</hi> is an Eſſential Branch, it may very well be ſuppoſed to be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under it: And we have
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:96884:47"/>
no reaſon to depart from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and more reſtrained Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Whatſoever things are pure.</hi> Moreover <hi>Sanctum</hi> is no other than <hi>Separatum,</hi> (as <hi>Grotius</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,) a thing that is ſeparated and ſet apart from common and impure Uſes, and Conſecrated to the Service of God. And thus Sanctity is oppoſed in Scripture to Filthineſs or Pollution. Hence it is that the Righteouſneſs of the Saints is compared to [<hi>Fine Linnen, Clean and White; for the fine Linnen is the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Saints,</hi> Revel. 19.8.] in oppoſition to the Impurities of Sin and Vice, which are denoted by <hi>[Filthy Garments,]</hi> Zech. 3.4. where <hi>Joſhua</hi> being Clothed with Filthy Garments, the Angel ſays, <hi>Take away the Filthy Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from him. And unto him he ſaid, Behold, I have cauſed thine Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to paſs from thee, and I will
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:96884:48"/>
Cloth thee with change of Raiment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Purity then that St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us here to, is no other than an Eſſential Part and Branch of the Divine Life, whereby we have ſo perfect and full a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over all our Senſual Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and all the Delights and Allurements of Fleſh and Blood, that they may not in the leaſt hinder our Union and Conjunction with God, nor by groſs and material Steams and Suffuſions intercept our ſight of that Eternal Pulchritude of the Divine Nature, to which we ought always to have an Eye, and direct all our Actions.</p>
               <p>Hence the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> ſpeak ſo much of their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Virtues, whereby they cleared the Mind from all thoſe irregular Motions that were raiſed from the Objects of Senſe, or ſprung from Corporeal Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:96884:48"/>
And indeed the whole Scope and Deſign of their Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Death, a Dying to our Earthly Paſſions, Appetites and Deſires, and a weaning the Soul from an inordinate Love of the Fleſh, and a through Purgation from all Carnal and Senſual Luſts, that they might behold <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with a pure Mind the unſpotted and incorrupted Deity.</p>
               <p>But whatever they aimed at is more clearly and fully made known to us in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, wherein we are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Mortifie our Members which are upon the Earth,</hi> Coloſſ. 3.5. <hi>i. e.</hi> our Earthly Luſts and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which ſpring from too near a Communication and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſion to theſe our Terreſtrial Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſuch as <hi>Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, inordinate Affection, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Concupiſcence, and Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:96884:49"/>
which is Idolatry.</hi> And to incourage them to this ſo indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible a Duty, the Apoſtle uſes theſe two Arguments; the firſt is in <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. <hi>For which things ſake, the Wrath of God cometh on the Children of Diſobedience, i. e.</hi> upon thoſe who would not be perſuaded nor wrought upon by the Motives and Arguments of the Goſpel to Change and Reform their Lives. The other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is taken from the Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they had engaged themſelves in, <hi>Verſe</hi> 8. <hi>But now, you alſo put off all theſe, Anger, Wrath, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Blaſphemy, Filthy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation out of your Mouth, q. d.</hi> You that now have given up your Names to Chriſt, and make Profeſſion of his Religion, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but know that Chriſtianity gives no Allowance to any of theſe Impurities and Pollutions, but calls Men to an Imitation of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:96884:49"/>
God who is the higheſt Purity. Wherefore there is an Indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Obligation lying upon all Chriſtians to put off and lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all ſuch Corrupt Luſts and Affections. And again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. <hi>The Night is far ſpent, the Day is at hand, let us therefore caſt off the Works of Darkneſs, and let us put on the Armour of Light. Let us walk honeſtly as in the Day, not in Rioting and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strife and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying. But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make not proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Fleſh to fulfil the Luſts thereof.</hi> By the Day is meant the Time of the Goſpel or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity appearing to the World: And by the Night is underſtood that State and Condition of Sin and Vice, wherein the World lay before the appearing of this Great Light. Now as the Light
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:96884:50"/>
is a pure and bright Subſtance, and the Goſpel which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, ſuch wherein is no Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at all, ſo it behoves us to Aſſimilate our ſelves to it in Works of Purity and Sanctity, and to have no more to do with any of the Deeds of Sin and Vice, which befit only the Spirits of Night and Darkneſs. And for our Encouragement herein, we ought,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſet before our Eyes that ſublime Copy and Example of Purity and Holineſs which is ſet forth in the Life of our Bleſſed Saviour: Who, though he were ſubject to all the harmleſs Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Infirmities of Mortality, (being made like unto his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in all things, Sin only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,) yet kept both his Body and Soul as a Pure Habitation of Righteouſneſs and Temple Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:96884:50"/>
wholly unto God; into which he never ſuffered any thing that was defiled and polluted at any time to enter. Though he Converſed with all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and his Behaviour was free and open, yet he taſted as little of Bodily Delights and Pleaſures as ever did any Man in the World. Yea even where they were allowable, he carefully ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from them, to teach us Self-denyal and Mortification, and to ſhew us, that though we live in the Body, and have an intimate Union with it, yet we may keep it under Subjection, and ſo regulate all its Motions and Affections, that our whole Man may be a fit Receptacle and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation for God to take up his Abode in. Therefore foreſeeing the danger how eaſily Men are betrayed by the ſecret Whiſpers and charming Inſinuations of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:96884:51"/>
theſe Earthly Bodies to which they are united, like a Faithful Friend he Admoniſhes them, in <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. <hi>To take heed <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> leſt at any time their hearts be overcharged, i. e.</hi> burdened and preſſed down with Surfeiting and Drunkenneſs, and the Cares of this Life, which like a heavy weight under which they are not able to ſtir, keep and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them from lifting up their Souls to God. For, the Souls of Men though they are confined to Bodies of Earth, and ſo at the preſent Inhabitants of this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible World, yet are made with ſuch Capacities as to live with God in Heaven: but by a too free indulging to their Bodies and Corporeal Affections, they are fatally tied and chained down to the Earth; and though they may now and then make ſome little Efforts and faint Attempts
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:96884:51"/>
to aſcend to thoſe higher Regions, yet it will be utterly impoſſible till they are perfectly diſentang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and diſengaged from the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and delights of Senſe. And leſt this Faithful Admonition of our Lord and Saviour ſhould not be ſufficient to keep us at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the enſnaring Ineſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Fleſh and Blood, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.8. <hi>That it is only the pure in Heart that ſhall ſee God.</hi> The Philoſophers tell us, that all like is known by its like, and if there were not ſomething that were <hi>Congenerous</hi> and Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gous to Light in the Eye, the whole World would be to us in a ſtate of Darkneſs: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, unleſs the Soul be purified and cleanſed from all dark and bodily Affections, and become in ſome meaſure inlightned where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may reſemble God, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it ſhould ever ſee him.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:96884:52"/>
Therefore our Bleſſed Saviour giving us ſo illuſtrious an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all Purity, Temperance and Chaſtity, and ſo earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending the ſame to all his Followers, not only ſhews us the Abſolute Neceſſity of the Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of our Bodily Luſts and Corruptions, but alſo the Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of attaining to ſuch a ſtate wherein all the Motions of the Body may be brought into a due ſubordination to our more Divine Powers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are to conſider that this Purity is indiſpenſibly neceſſary for the attaining Divine Wiſdom and Knowledg. There is nothing ſo much darkens our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, clouds our Judgments, and beſots all the Rational Faculties of our Souls, as the bathing and ſinking our ſelves into Bodily De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and Pleaſures. For as the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:96884:52"/>
Corrupt Life of the Body grows and increaſes, ſo proportionably the Divine and Heavenly Life dies and is extinguiſhed, and we loſe all ſenſe, and relliſh, and taſt of Heavenly things. And it is impoſſible it ſhould be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for (as <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 3.31.) <hi>He that is of the Earth, is Earthly, and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the Earth.</hi> And while the Earthly Principle is only alive in us, it will Act according to its Nature, and we are ruled and guided by its Motions and Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: And we know that this [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] Natural Man, <hi>Receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. There is a Divine quickneſs and ſagacity that ſprings up in a puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Soul, whereby it readily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends, and has a Vital Senſe of Heavenly and Divine Things, which they that are ſunk and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:96884:53"/>
loſt in Bodily Luſts and Paſſions are perfect ſtrangers to. And not only Philoſophy but Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity tells us of Two diſtinct Principles in Man, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls by the Name <hi>of the inner and outer Man:</hi> And theſe Two have their different Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Tendencies and Deſigns. The <hi>outer Man</hi> is the Inheritance we derive from <hi>Adam,</hi> which he elſewhere, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. ſtiles, <hi>[the old Man,]</hi> which is to be Crucified with Chriſt, <hi>That the Body of Sin might be deſtroyed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerve Sin.</hi> Now this <hi>outer Man,</hi> or <hi>old Adam,</hi> is only the Corrupt Life of the Body, which leads to all manner of Impurity and Vice, and is to be Mortified and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. But the <hi>inner Man</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as <hi>Plotinus</hi> calls it,) the <hi>true Man,</hi> whoſe very Form and Nature conſiſts in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:96884:53"/>
pure and unſpotted Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Holineſs; it is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Lord from Heaven; and as is the Heavenly <hi>Adam,</hi> ſuch are they that are Heavenly. Now each of theſe Two Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Life is very diligent and induſtrious to Diffuſe and Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate it ſelf; and therefore is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting to offer all fit and inſinuating Arguments to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote its own Intereſt.</p>
               <p>Hence the Apoſtle St. <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 3.15. tells us of a Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that is, <hi>Earthly, Senſual,</hi> and <hi>Deviliſh:</hi> Now this Wiſdom is the Genuine Production, and true Offspring of the Bodily Life: 'tis the Thoughts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the <hi>Old Adam,</hi> and is ſaid to be <hi>Earthly,</hi> becauſe all its Deſigns and Purpoſes are laid out and contrived merely for this Earth and World wherein we live. And it is <hi>Senſual,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:96884:54"/>
it ſtudies only for the Gratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Senſe and the Animal or Brutiſh Life: And <hi>Deviliſh,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as only upholds the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's Kingdom, and promotes his Reign and Empire throughout the World. But then he ſays, <hi>Verſe</hi> 17. that there is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Wiſdom that deſcends from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</hi> from the Father of Lights; and as it derives from Heaven, ſo it is ſtill endeavouring to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and lift up the Soul thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. This is that <hi>Wiſdom</hi> which is communicated to the Soul from the Spirit of Chriſt, and being it ſelf ſo Pure and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, will not dwell in a Body that is Polluted with all Carnal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and Defilements. And if we ſhould look upon the Effects of Senſuality and Debauchery, as they are Daily viſible before our Eyes, we ſhall find that nothing does more Corrupt and Spoil our
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:96884:54"/>
Rational Powers. There are none that ſpend their whole Time in Gratifying their Carnal Luſts, but their Underſtandings grow Dull and Heavy, and loſe their Briskneſs and Livelineſs; their Memories are Treacherous and Decayed; and their Fanſies and Imaginations ſerve only as a Stage to Repreſent and Act over again their paſt Filthineſs and Pollutions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Without this Purity of Fleſh and Spirit, there is no U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our Souls with God. Union and Communion with God are the greateſt Bleſſings the Soul of Man can partake of: But none can think that God will dwell in a Charnel-houſe, or take up his Habitation among Dead Bones. And thoſe that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to Bodily Pleaſures, and drown themſelves in Senſual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:96884:55"/>
in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſenſe are no better than Dead, even while they Live an Earthly Life, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6. We Read indeed of Spirits converſing among the Tombs, but God will have no Society with the Dead: <hi>It is the Living alone that praiſe him, and declare his Truth.</hi> There can be no Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe nor Communion between God and ſuch a Man's Soul that has no Life ſtirring in it, but what is the very Life and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Spirits of Darkneſs, who are the moſt of all alienated and eſtranged from him. He that is <hi>joined unto the Lord, is one Spirit,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. that is, there is ſuch an intire Conſent and Agreement between ſuch an One and God, that he wills nothing and deſires nothing but what God wills and deſires. But there is is no Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Conſent, or Concord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:96884:55"/>
God and that Perſon that is joined and tied to his Bodily Luſts and Corrupt Affections. The pure Virgin-Chaſtity of the Soul is Violated and Defiled by Proſtituting it to the Foul Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of Corporeal Pleaſures; ſo that it is a kind of Spiritual Fornication or Adultery.</p>
               <p>Now to the intent we may all endeavour to attain this Purity that God requires, and which it is our Intereſt to purſue, let us</p>
               <p n="1">1. Abſtract our Souls as much as we can from Senſe and Senſible Delights &amp; Pleaſures. Even a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could ſay,<note place="margin">Simpl. in Epictet, p. <hi>257. &amp; 78.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>That there is nothing more Deſtructive and Pernicious to the Soul, than to give it ſelf up to Bodily Pleaſures;</hi> becauſe they do as it were nail and bind it faſt to the Earth, that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:96884:56"/>
it hath no might nor ſtrength to lift up it ſelf towards Heaven. Therefore our Bleſſed Saviour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring us to pluck out the Right Eye, and cut off the Right Hand, would have us do Violence to the Unruly Affections of the Body, and bring them low, and abate their Power by ſuch a due Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that they may never betray us to Act againſt Reaſon and Conſcience. If we would endeavour to ſet a little looſe from our Bodies, and withdraw our Hearts from Senſual Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and deny the Cravings of our Carnal Appetites, we ſhould not only find a mighty Peace and Satisfaction within our own Breaſts, but be more fitted to Converſe with the God of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us frequently repreſent to our ſelves that pure ſtate of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:96884:56"/>
Angels in the upper Regions; and that ſuch a ſtate cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with Carnal Impurities.</p>
               <p>Heaven is no <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, filled with Carnal and Senſual, but Divine and Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Joys and Pleaſures. The time will quickly come when we ſhall be ſtript of theſe Earthly Bodies, which we now ſo fondly Dote upon, and Careſs and Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the fulfilling all their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure Luſts. And therefore it were our Wiſdom to ſeparate and disjoin our Minds from their too near Intimacy and Familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with them; and to dwell of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and much in our Thoughts upon that Future State in which all theſe Corporeal Pleaſures will be at an end. Then we ſhould not be ſo unwilling and uneaſie to leave our Bodies, but ſhould put them off with a full Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that we ſhould not be left
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:96884:57"/>
Naked, but Clothed upon with our Houſe from Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider how infinitely Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Luſts and Affections debaſe our Souls, and render them Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh. Every Chriſtians Body is or ought to be God's Temple, wherein he dwells and makes his Reſidence; and it is a great Abuſe and Profanation of this his Temple to make it a place for nothing but Carnal Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Pollutions, and in our Saviour's Language, <hi>Turning it into a Den of Thieves,</hi> and which is all one, a Receptacle for thoſe Unclean Spirits which ſollicit Men to all Impurities. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let every Man reflect with himſelf, that he has a Soul that was made in the Image of God, and that Chriſt came into the World to renew in it his Holy and Pure Image; and therefore
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:96884:57"/>
that he ought not to turn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a Beaſt by Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Debauchery, and Laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. For how unreaſonable a thing is it, that any Man ſhould thus fall from the Excellency of his Nature, which is fitted to Converſe with God, by Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating himſelf only with his Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh part! that he ſhould ſo far derogate from his Native Glory, that whereas he was firſt made in Honour, he ſhould be only now fit to be compared with the Beaſts that periſh!</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, Conſider that this is the Field of Virtue, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lies true Fortitude and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in over-coming all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Allurements and Ineſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Fleſh and Blood. This is the Province which God has given every Man to undertake, and wherein he who is <hi>the firſt and the laſt,</hi> (if we be not Faithleſs
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:96884:58"/>
and Hypocritical,) will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly give us a compleat Victory and Conqueſt. Here lies the Gallantry of a Noble Mind, which ſcorns to be enfeebled with Fleſh and Blood, but ſoars aloft, and is impatient till it attain its Crown of Glory. For certainly 'tis the inordinacy of our Corporeal Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections that Effeminates our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and makes them ſo nice and tender as not to endure or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go any thing for the ſake of God and Virtue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Whatſoever things are lovely.</head>
               <p>After the Apoſtle's Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to things pure, he proceeds to things that <hi>are lovely.</hi> For unleſs our Minds are firſt purified from all Earthly and Senſual Drugs, we are in no fit diſpoſition to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Intellectual Lovelineſs and Beauty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:96884:58"/>
                  <hi>Whatſoever things are lovely,</hi> that is, Attractive and Deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſuch as carry an inward Beauty in them, and are ſuited and accommodated to win Favour and Friendſhip, and by their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging Sweetneſs bind as it were the Minds of others to us. For, as there is an Inward and Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Deformity in all Vitious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo there is a Natural Pulchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in thoſe that are Virtuous: Which Beauty and Lovelineſs wherever it may be ſcattered, and in whatever ſubject it may reſide, is only a Ray or Emanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God who is the Original Fountain of all Pulchritude and Beauty. Now the Great Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty here will be in diſcerning what things are Lovely and Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and what are not: For though there be never ſo many Amiable and Deſirable Objects in the World, yet unleſs we
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:96884:59"/>
have ſome <hi>Criterium,</hi> ſomething into which they may be reſolved, and which is able to diſtinguiſh them from others, and to diſcern True from Falſe and Adulterate Beauties, it will ſignifie little to us.</p>
               <p>To this Purpoſe therefore we ought to know, that there is an Intellectual Beauty and Loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as well as that which is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and Corporeal. Hence <hi>Plato</hi> that Contemplative and Thinking Philoſopher, ſpeaks of a twofold <hi>Venus,</hi> the one is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Celeſtial <hi>Venus,</hi> which is nothing but the fair Pulchritude of the Divine Nature it ſelf, which though it dwell in thoſe upper Regions, yet has made very viſible Impreſſions of it ſelf upon the whole Creation; and has contracted and cloſely ſealed that Beauty which lies diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and diffuſed in all Parts of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:96884:59"/>
the Univerſe, upon all the Orders of Intellectual Beings. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a kind of Common and Harlotry <hi>Venus,</hi> which deriving only from the Body, and a branch of the Animal Life, draws down the Soul to what is merely Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal, and mingling with it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files and pollutes it.</p>
               <p>Now when St. <hi>Paul</hi> Exhorts here to things that <hi>are lovely,</hi> he does not mean what is Grateful and Acceptable to this Earthly Love, but that which is agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſymmetral, (as I may ſo ſpeak,) with Divine and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Love. So that things are to be accounted ſo far Lovely, as they more or leſs partake of and reſemble that Uncreated and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Pulchritude above. And whatever things may exalt the Soul to a Participation of this Primitive and Original Beauty,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:96884:60"/>
the practice of them is called by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3.4. <hi>The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning of the hidden Man of the Heart,</hi> whoſe incorruptible Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Excellency is ſeen and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in a meek and calm Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. And ſurely nothing in the World can be more Beautiful and Lovely than that which hath the moſt exact Symmetry and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity with that Archetypal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of Divine Lovelineſs and Beauty. Which was never made ſo viſible to Mortal Eyes, as it was in our Bleſſed Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, who being the expreſs I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Character of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Perſon, came on purpoſe to reſtore in Men that Beautiful reſemblance of the Great Author of their Being, which their Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous and Diſorderly Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions had Obliterated and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:96884:60"/>It is ſaid of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that they increaſed in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with God and Men: Of our Saviour we have it in <hi>Luke</hi> 2.52. that he <hi>increaſed in favour with God and Man.</hi> And of his Apoſtles it is written, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. <hi>Praiſing God, and having favour with all the People.</hi> Now ſurely the great things that purchaſed them this favour, was in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the doing and practiſing all ſuch things as were Lovely in the Eyes of all Virtuous Men. For what elſe could make our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and his Apoſtles appear ſuch excellent Perſons in the World, but only the doing of all grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and obliging things? They left great Obligations upon all Men.</p>
               <p>There are Two things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the Perſon of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our which will excellently well inſtruct us in what <hi>things are
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:96884:61"/>
lovely.</hi> For he is certainly the beſt Pattern we can imitate; and by beholding the fair Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and irreprehenſible Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Holy Life, we may learn in all general reſpects how to lead our own.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Obligingneſs of his Carriage and Deportment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Innocency of his Life and Actions. As for the firſt of theſe; Our Holy Lord was of the ſweeteſt Nature and Temper that ever was in the World. We uſually account it matter of Praiſe to a Perſon, that he is of a Fair and Obliging Temper: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold then a Deſcription of the beſt Nature that ever was Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Fleſh and Blood. Our bleſſed Maſter, (whoſe ſteps all Men are bound to follow,) was no Proud or Moroſe Perſon,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:96884:61"/>
Slighting, Undervaluing and Contemning others; but ſo Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Meek, that he diſdained not the Company of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and loweſt upon Earth to do them Good. Inſomuch as this free and excellent Temper of his drew upon him the Envy and Hatred of the Supercilious and Cenſorious Phariſees, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.2. they upbraid him, <hi>That he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Sinners and Eat with them;</hi> and he defends himſelf, <hi>That he came to call Sinners to Repentance.</hi> He did not think it below him to do good to the worſt of Men. For he knew himſelf ſent, and his Compaſſions extended to the Salvation of the Souls of the Meaneſt as well as the Greateſt Perſons: Being very ſenſible that God his Father, looked not upon Men as they were high or low in the World, but deſigned equally the Salvation of them all. We
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:96884:62"/>
read in <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.2. that there came a Leper to Chriſt: If he had come to the Phariſees, they would have bidden him ſtand off, becauſe he was Unclean; though they never conſidered the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs of their own Hearts, which made them appear as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and Polluted in God's Eyes, as poſſibly the Leper could be in theirs: <hi>But Jeſus put forth his Hand and touched him.</hi> He was as willing to Heal him, as the poor Leper was to be Cleanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Search but into the Goſpel, and you ſhall ſee ſuch Rays and Beams of Lovelineſs flow from our Saviour as cannot but poſſeſs your Souls with ſomething of that Mild and Amiable Glory. He was Courteous and Affable to all, and eaſie to be intreated to any Good Office that lay in his way. In <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.32. it is
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:96884:62"/>
ſaid, <hi>That when the Multitude had been long with him, and had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Eat, Jeſus had Compaſſion on them.</hi> They were in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, a place very unfit to procure Food; and they had a great way to go, and without ſome Relief might have fainted by the way. It is true, it was Chriſt's chief Buſineſs to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the Bread of Life to their Languiſhing Souls; but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered likewiſe the Infirmities of Humane Nature, and was will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuſtain their Bodies like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: From whence we ſee, that our Saviour had rather work a Miracle, than not be helpful to the Infirmities of Mankind. Nay where there was no abſolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, but only a matter of Courteſie and Good Nature, yet our Lord was willing to ſhew it; <hi>As when he turned Water into Wine at the Marriage in</hi> Canaa <hi>of</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:96884:63"/>
Galilee. All theſe Actions made his Soul appear with as clear and ſerene Lovelineſs, as his outward Viſage when his Face was Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the Sun in the Day of his Transfiguration.</p>
               <p>But the greateſt Sign of a good and excellent Nature was, his readineſs to paſs by Affronts and Diſgraces without the leaſt ſhew of Anger or Impatiency. In <hi>John</hi> 11.8. we read, that though the People a little before were ready to ſtone him, yet he goes again to teach and inſtruct them; as if he had clean forgotten the Wrong they intended againſt him. Yea, when that Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Traytor came by a Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Kiſs to betray him into the Hands of his implacable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; though he had in the moſt ſhameful manner Violated all the Ties of Friendſhip, (being one of them that familiarly Eat of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:96884:63"/>
his Bread,) yet he gives him no harſher Language than that of Friend. And when he was Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſet at Naught by <hi>Herod</hi>'s Men of War, he never uttered an Impatient Word, nor was ever heard to Revile thoſe that Reviled him. Nor was he ever moved with Anger againſt any, unleſs it were for their obſtinate Unbelief. How Amiable and Lovely was the Perſon of our Lord and Saviour! How Divine and Godlike was his Carriage! The Foundation of all true Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip lies in Virtue, and here we may ſee Virtue in her moſt Exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Luſtre; all thoſe winning Graces which may Conciliate Friendſhip, Benevolence and Kindneſs. There was nothing that can poſſibly render any Man Grateful and Acceptable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but it was found in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:96884:64"/>He always went about doing Good, and like the Sun ſhedding a Salutary Influence even upon the Unthankful and Evil. If he met with any that were troubled with Bodily Pains, and deſirous of his Help, he gave them Eaſe; if in Doubts and Perplexities, he Reſolved them; ſhewing to the World that he came to bring Health and Happineſs both to Soul and Body. As for thoſe black and ill-favoured Paſſions of Malice and Revenge, they never had any place in his Heart, which was conſtantly inflamed with Love, whereby he forgot and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave the Injuries he received. When the <hi>Samaritans</hi> rejected him, and would give him no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, his Apoſtles in their thoughts had already devoted them to Deſtruction, and want only their Maſter's Permiſſion to call for Fire from Heaven to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:96884:64"/>
them, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.54. But Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was of a better and milder Temper, and tells them, <hi>That his Buſineſs was not to deſtroy Life, but to ſave it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Think with your ſelves now; Was there ever a more Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Obliging Nature in the World than that of Chriſt Jeſus? Was the Divinity it ſelf with all its inconceivable Beauty and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ever more Conſpicuouſly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to Fleſh and Blood, than in the Perſon of our Bleſſed Lord? Theſe things were <hi>Lovely</hi> in him, and the Practice of them made him win the Reſpect and Favour of all Virtuous Perſons wherever he came. And doubtleſs, the Apoſtle when he bids us mind things that are <hi>Lovely,</hi> means all theſe Acts of Love and Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Philanthropy which we have ſeen in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:96884:65"/>2. The Innocence of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Life and Actions. As his Converſe was Obliging, and his Deportment exceeding Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo his Life was Innocent, and never Blemiſhed with any Sin. All his Actions were ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the moſt exact Rules and Meaſures of Virtue. For his moſt implacable Enemies could never Tax him with any Spot in his Life, or with any Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Deed during his whole Abode upon Earth. He was indeed the moſt uſeful Perſon that ever Lived in the World. For though a Man have never ſo excellent a Spirit, yet if this be wholly ſhut up within himſelf, it falls ſhort of our Saviour's Pattern. And if Self-intereſt and Self-deſign be the Motive of Acting, whatever proceeds thence, loſes all its Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Lovelineſs. But the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Saviour's Soul, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:96884:65"/>
the Exaltedneſs of that Divine Life that was in him, made him Sagacious, and of a quick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception between things that were really Lovely, and ſuch as were Ugly and Deformed. And theſe Two things rendred our Bleſſed Lord the moſt Exact and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Pattern of a Lovely and Excellent Nature that ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared upon the Stage of the Earth. Now though we have given a General Delineation of what is <hi>Lovely,</hi> from the Life of our Bleſſed Saviour, yet perhaps it may be more eaſily apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if we reduce theſe General Obſervations into ſome more Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and Diſtinct Heads. He therefore that would do things that are really <hi>Lovely,</hi> and come up as near to the Similitude of the Life of our Holy Lord and Maſter as he can, muſt Breath nothing but Love and Good-will to the World: And</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:96884:66"/>1. He muſt be of eaſie Acceſs, and ready without any Contempt or Diſdain of any Man's Perſon to afford his Aſſiſtance as far as he is able, to the Meaneſt both in Word and Deed, according as he ſhall find their Neceſſities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: Chearfully affording Counſel to the Afflicted, and binding up the Broken-Hearted, and without any Bitterneſs or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, or Baſe and Shameful Flattery, making his Converſe with others Sweet and Delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that would do things <hi>Lovely,</hi> muſt take care even in the Reprehenſions and Rebukes of others for what is Amiſs, that it be done with ſo much Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and Paſſionate Sweetneſs, that thoſe whoſe Sins are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, may clearly ſee, it is their Good, and Benefit, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:96884:66"/>
Advantage, that is only aimed at. For otherwiſe Men's Minds may rather be Exaſperated than Healed, when Truth it ſelf in ſuch a Caſe is delivered with too great a Sharpneſs and Harſhneſs. Men do not uſually care to hear of their Faults; but when they ſhall be laid open and diſcovered with Bitterneſs, Contempt and Scorn, it is ſo far from caſting an healing Influence upon their Souls, that it provokes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames their Minds.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He that would exactly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which is <hi>Lovely,</hi> muſt provide that in doing Kindneſſes, he do not Upbraid and Shame them upon whom he intends to confer them. There are many Perſons of that tender and modeſt Diſpoſition, who bluſh and are aſhamed either to ask or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe Kindneſſes which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:96884:67"/>
they want. And then, the doing things <hi>Lovely</hi> obliges a Man ſo to aſſiſt them in whatever it be, as may leaſt of all make them Aſhamed.</p>
               <p>Now by what has been ſaid from General Obſervations drawn from the Life of our Saviour, and by theſe few Particulars, we may competently enough under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what the Apoſtle means by Exhorting us to the Practice of <hi>Whatſoever things are Lovely.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Whatſoever things are of good Report.</head>
               <p>The laſt inſtance of Virtue the Apoſtle makes uſe of, is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade us to the practice of ſuch things as are of <hi>good Report:</hi> By which we are taught to think of and do all ſuch things as may purchaſe us a Good Name, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:96884:67"/>
Eſteem, and Reputation, among ſuch as are Virtuous, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the differences of things. Now from hence we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all things are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different and alike. There is a Natural Bravery, Excellency and Becomingneſs, in ſome Actions, and there is a Baſeneſs and Filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in others, whether we will or not. For the Difference and Diſtinction of things does not depend upon our Wills; nor can we change their Natures as we pleaſe. Indeed to the Atheiſt and to ſuch as do not believe the Exiſtence of any Spiritual Being, but reſolve all things into Dead and Senſeleſs Matter, there is no Diſtinction or Difference of things, but only what Men are pleaſed to make; and then as oft as Wicked Men get into Power,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:96884:68"/>
they may make things Vitious in themſelves to be called by the Name of Virtues. But ſince there is a God, (and none but Fools can think otherwiſe,) we are aſſured that all Virtue derives from him, and is a participation of his Image and Nature, and Conſequently that there is an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Difference in the Nature of things. And God hath Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied out and Engraven this his Image upon the Souls of Men, whereby all Men that have a due uſe of their Faculties, have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the differences of Good and Evil deeply Sealed upon their Minds, and they cannot change them at their Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Hence it comes to paſs that ſuch Actions as are Conformable and Agreeable to thoſe Intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Laws and Principles which God has fixed in our Minds, they are Virtuous and Praiſe-worthy;
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:96884:68"/>
and ſuch as are otherwiſe, they are Deteſtable and Vile, and have an inward Turpitude ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſt to them. And ſince all Men have the Laws of Virtue written on their Hearts, and are ſenſible that they ought to walk according to theſe, there will Naturally ariſe an Eſteem for thoſe Perſons who walk the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt according to theſe Rules. And this which we call Eſteem or Fame, and a Good Name or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, is indeed a part of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Virtue; when Men are Applauded and Praiſed, when they fulfil the end of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Act like Rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures according to thoſe Laws and Preſcriptions the Eternal Mind has interwoven in the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Frame and Contexture of their Souls.</p>
               <p>True it is, Fame and Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a thing that is mightily
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:96884:69"/>
ſought after, even by thoſe that are no great Admirers of the ſtrictneſs of Virtue; and there is in all Men a ſecret Deſire and Tendency towards the Embalm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Conſecrating their Names to after Ages. Of which no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſon can be given, but that there are ſome ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions and Natural Preſages of a State of Immortality after this Life, in all Men's Minds. There is ſomething that whiſpers to them, and mixes it ſelf with all their Thoughts and Actions, that they have ſomething in them that ſhall ſurvive their Aſhes, and Live and Act when their Bodies are Dead and Rotten in the Grave. And from hence they Naturally Affect and Deſire a Continuation of themſelves, and a kind of Immortality in this Life. And this ſets them upon thoſe various Ways and Methods
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:96884:69"/>
of the Purchaſe and Acquiſition of it; ſome by Valour and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Actions, others by Honour, and ſome by the increaſe of their Poſterity: Which evidently ſhews the Deſires and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all Men to continue and live for ever upon Earth, at leaſt in their Fame, and Names, and Memory, although they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from it as to their Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Beings. Thus we Read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.11. of ſome whoſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thought</hi> was, <hi>That their Houſes ſhould continue for ever, and they call their Lands after their own Names, i. e.</hi> Many Men ſeeing that themſelves are Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and quickly Die, yet deſire to perpetuate their Names, and that their Memory ſhould Live after them: Whereas this only ſhews, that there is implanted in Men Naturally a Senſe, that there are things of good Report,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:96884:70"/>
which will procure Fame, and Eſteem, and a Good Name, while they Live here, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue it when they are gone from hence: But they miſtook in the Ways and Means of Attaining it.</p>
               <p>But now true Religion aſſures us, that it is only the ſincere Practice of Virtue that will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance a Good Name, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Eſteem here, and continue it after Death; according to that of the Scripture, <hi>The Righteous ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi> It is true, many a Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man's Name is Remembred, but then 'tis to his Infamy and Diſgrace. Therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7. <hi>The Name of the Wicked ſhall Rot, i. e.</hi> it ſhall be as Offenſive and Unpleaſant as a Dead and Rotten Carkaſs. We Read of a Covetous and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous <hi>Judas</hi> who ſold his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:96884:70"/>
but we Deteſt and Abhor his Memory: And of a Cruel and Bloody <hi>Herod,</hi> but with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as keen a Paſſion as thoſe ſorrowful Mothers felt at the Death of their little Infants. Thus every Wicked Man, if he be at all Remembred, 'tis with ſome Infamous Character and Note of Diſgrace; as that he was a Profane, and Debauch'd, or a Laſcivious, Covetous, or Unjuſt Perſon; and it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that our Names Periſh for Ever, and we deſcend into a Common and Ignoble Grave, than to be thus Remembred.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are informed, that the proper Judges of things of <hi>good Report,</hi> are Virtuous and Wiſe Perſons. Among all thoſe things that are Valuable with Men, there is none, (or at leaſt ought not to be any,) of ſo high an
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:96884:71"/>
Eſteem as true Virtue; which being the Image of God Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated unto Man, it follows, that things are only ſo far of <hi>good Report</hi> as they are Virtuous. And hence it is, that the true Judg of what is Virtuous, and what is not, muſt be the Wiſe and Virtuous Man himſelf. For he being plentifully endued with, and perfectly awakened into this high and exalted Principle of Life, he preſently feels and knows, and has a quick taſt and relliſh of what is agreeable to that Divine Life which his Soul is ſo throughly poſſeſſed of: And being perfectly Dead to all Senſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Affections which may Cloud or Diſtruct his Judgment, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly diſcerns the leaſt Blemiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Corruptions of Life, and ſo becomes perfectly inabled to determin what is Laudable and Praiſe worthy, and of <hi>good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port:</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:96884:71"/>
This Internal Senſe of his being as fitly qualified to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern its proper Objects, as the clear Eye is to diſcern Light and Colours. But as for Men of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Souls, and Wicked Lives, they are no more able to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min and define things of <hi>good Report,</hi> than Swines are to Judg of the Symmetry of a Beautiful Picture.</p>
               <p>So that when we ſpeak of things of <hi>good Report,</hi> we muſt take our Meaſures from what the beſt and wiſeſt Perſons in all Times and Ages have accounted ſo. And for a Man to underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the Judgment of ſuch who have jointly and unanimouſly concluded from that inward Senſe they have of Virtue, that ſuch and ſuch Actions are Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and of <hi>good Report,</hi> and the contrary Diſhoneſt and Baſe, is
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:96884:72"/>
no better than a great piece of Pride and Arrogance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He that purchaſes a good Name by Virtue, he purchaſes the greateſt Treaſure that is to be had in this World. Therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.1. <hi>That a good Name is rather to be choſen than great Riches.</hi> Becauſe Riches are ſomething without us, and do not at all contribute to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Soul; but things of <hi>good Report</hi> being nothing but the effects of Virtue, and of that Life which is the true Being of the Soul, they are inſeparable from it. Moreover the Virtuous Man cannot fail by ſuch Actions of making many Friends, which are, (as <hi>Boethius</hi> ſpeaks,) <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſiſſimum divitiarum genus, The moſt pretious kind of Riches.</hi> And further, our good or ill Fame is not peremptorily confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:96884:72"/>
to this World, but paſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us into the next: And eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man by his good or bad Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour brings a good or ill Report of himſelf in the Regions of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, before he comes to dwell and converſe with them. If we be Wicked, we are as much ſcorned there, and our Names as Hateful, as the Names of <hi>Judas</hi> or <hi>Herod.</hi> The Angels and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Spirits quickly know what we are, (for thoſe diſcerning Spirits are not eaſily deceived,) and the Fame of our Doings ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives to them before we leave the World. Thoſe Bleſſed Spirits are ſaid to Rejoyce at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of a Sinner, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.10. which is an evident Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that our good or evil Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour readily comes to their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and Cognizance. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 'tis no ſmall dammage to have an ill Report among thoſe who
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:96884:73"/>
ſhould Aſſiſt us and Miniſter to us in our Wants and Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By doing things of <hi>good Report,</hi> we conſult not only our own Eſteem, but the Credit of that Holy Religion we profeſs. It is ſaid, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17. that the Sin of <hi>Elie</hi>'s Sons made <hi>Men ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the Offering of the Lord.</hi> Their Sinful and Vitious manner of Living brought an ill Report upon themſelves, and it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounded likewiſe to God's Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and cauſed Men to Slight and Deſpiſe and Undervalue his Worſhip and Service. So it is with us, when we deſervedly by ſome Evil Action bring an ill Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port upon our ſelves; the Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour lights not only upon us, that reflects on God, and that Holy Religion that we profeſs. Thus it is ſaid likewiſe of <hi>David,</hi>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:96884:73"/>
2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14. <hi>That by his Sin he had given cauſe to the Enemies of the Lord to Blaſpheme.</hi> When they ſaw ſo Holy a Man as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> fall ſo foully into Sin, they would be apt to deſpiſe Religion it ſelf, and cry out, <hi>Is this the fruit of Religion?</hi> And when thoſe that are Chriſtians ſhall commit Diſhoneſt and Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Actions; when they ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelves in the Practice of Open and Scandalous Sins, Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Prophane Perſons are apt to traduce and ſpeak Evil of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelf. Thus our Holy Lord and his Religion which he Sealed with his own Blood is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and Contemned through the Bad Lives of thoſe that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it. It ſhould therefore be our Care to conſult the Credit of Religion, and to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Lovely, (as it is) in all Men's Eyes, by our practiſing all
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:96884:74"/>
ſuch things as are favoured and well eſteem'd by all the Lovers of Virtue. When we go to the Houſe of God, and tread his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Courts, we ſhould uſe no light and trifling Behaviour, but compoſe both our Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with that Awful Reverence as becomes the Preſence of God and his Holy Angels. Our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion ſhould be grave, ſerious and fervent, without any Affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, or vain deſire of Oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And we ſhould make it appear that our Hearts are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly touched and inflamed with that unimitable Love of Chriſt in Dying for the World, by our frequent Communicating of his Bleſſed Body and Blood. For theſe things, as they are mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>good Report,</hi> and will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly procure favour and eſteem, ſo they ſhew that Religion has ſomething that is really valuable
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:96884:74"/>
in it, and that Chriſtianity is the choiceſt Wiſdom that ever was communicated to Mankind.</p>
               <p>If we would therefore do things that are of <hi>good Report,</hi> we ought</p>
               <p n="1">1. To put in Practice all theſe forementioned Virtues, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe is Laudable and Praiſe-worthy. The Honour and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of Religion is never better ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, than by a due Regard to its Sacred Laws and Inſtitutions. Though we profeſs to own Truth, yet if we are always wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and unſettled, and toſſed about with every wind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin; if we are not true to our Words and Promiſes, but Falſifie and Diſſemble and Lie one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, we ſeem not to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jealous of her Honour. Nor can we be ſaid to conſult the Credit of our Holy Profeſſion, while by
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:96884:75"/>
the Lightneſs, Vanity, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becomingneſs of our Actions, we expreſs no Veneration for it. Who can believe that we are in Earneſt when we talk of Juſtice, and yet do not endeavour to frame our Converſations by that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Rule of doing as we would be done by? A Diſcourſe of the Sanctity and Purity of Angels will little affect others, while we our ſelves wallow in the Mire and Sink of all Carnal Luſts and Pollutions. Should we tell Men of an Internal Beauty and Loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in things, yet it would be but Words ſpent to no purpoſe, unleſs we demonſtrate our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of it by doing lovely and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging Actions. It is the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of our Duty that conciliates Reverence and Eſteem to Religion, and promotes a fair Reputation to our ſelves, when Men ſhall ſee that we are in Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:96884:75"/>
by our unblamable Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations. Which is according to that ſound Admonition of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Having your Converſation honeſt among the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>that whereas they ſpeak againſt you as evil doers, they may by your good works which they ſhall behold, Glorifie God in the day of Viſitation.</hi> Notwithſtanding all the Malitious Cavils, and Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical Objections made againſt Religion, yet a true Chriſtian that walks anſwerably to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, muſt gain at the laſt a Repute and Eſteem from all that are Lovers of God and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If we would do things of <hi>good Report,</hi> and which may pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe us a good Name amongſt Men, we muſt carefully avoid, not only the open practice of Vice, but whatever may have
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:96884:76"/>
any ſuſpicion in the Minds of Men of Vice. And this is called by the Apoſtle, <hi>An abſtaining from all appearance of Evil,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.22. Whether that ſignifie from every ſort or kind of Evil, or from every thing that bears the likeneſs, appearance, or ſhew of a Sin. For he that will venture as near to the Confines and Borders of Sin as he can, ſeems to declare a Tacit Liking and Approbation of it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently expoſes himſelf to the hazard of being Betrayed and Surprized, and ſo of loſing his Credit and Reputation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Wary and Cautious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, (and ſuch it behoves eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man to be,) will ſtudiouſly avoid every thing that may cauſe the leaſt Jealouſie in the Hearts of others of his Sincerity.</p>
               <p>There are many things which are not directly Sinful, yet to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:96884:76"/>
who has not that Maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Ripeneſs of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may prove an occaſion of Stumbling and Falling, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not to be done by him who would acquire a good E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and Reputation. It is true, if a thing that is in it ſelf indifferent be, upon weighty Reaſons and Grounds commanded by Law; and another through Weakneſs is ſcandalized at the uſe of it, it is a thing which a good Chriſtian cannot help; and there is an Offence taken, but not given: Though it were to be wiſhed that there were as few of theſe Stumbling Blocks laid before Weaker Perſons, as may fairly conſiſt with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Intereſt of Religion it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He that would acquire a Good Name and Reputation, muſt
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:96884:77"/>
take care that in all his Actings with others he be ſincere; <hi>i. e.</hi> upon all Emergences, he muſt practiſe Virtue for Virtues ſake, becauſe it is in it ſelf the beſt and moſt deſirable thing in the World. For if in our Converſation we proceed upon Siniſter Ends, and that Self-advantage and Intereſt be the Meaſure of our Actions, beſides that it redounds to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit of Religion, it caſts a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace upon us, and we ſo far de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate from the Principles of true Virtue, as Selfiſhneſs is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Actions. And the Reaſon is, becauſe he that makes a fair ſhow of ſome Virtuous Actions, merely to compaſs Self-Advantage, does hereby mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly declare, that if it were not for this Private and Self Love, he would not do them; which the generality of Mankind muſt needs look upon as a groſs piece
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:96884:77"/>
of Hypocriſie and Diſſimulation; than which nothing can be a greater Enemy to our true Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Reputation.</p>
               <p>Thus you have an Account of the ſeveral Virtues, to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of which the Apoſtle ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly Exhorts us. And he that has any Care for the Peace of his Conſcience in this Life, and his Eternal Happineſs hereafter, will carefully think on theſe things. Which that we may all do, He who is the Author and Finiſher of our Faith grant to us; to whom be all Honour and Glory both now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:96884:78"/>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:96884:78"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF <hi>Sincerity.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 1.47.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, in whom is no guile.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE Words our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſpake of <hi>Nathana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> who is reckoned one of the Twelve Apoſtles, though called by another Name; for we find him expreſsly mentioned with them, <hi>John</hi> 21.2. This Perſon being brought by <hi>Philip</hi> to Jeſus, when he was come
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:96884:79"/>
within diſtance or hearing, Chriſt ſays, <hi>Behold an</hi> Iſraelite <hi>indeed, in whom is no guile.</hi> As if our Lord had ſaid, See here a Man of that Integrity, Simplicity, and Sincerity, which is highly valued and prized in God's ſight. And though this were ſpoken parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of that Apoſtle, yet it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs us in this Great and Weighty Truth, <hi>That Sincerity is the great Accompliſhment and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of a Chriſtian in God's ſight.</hi> For it is no new thing for true Chriſtians to be called in Scripture by the Name of <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites:</hi> For St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes it ſo in more than one place in plain terms, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6. <hi>They are not all</hi> Iſrael <hi>which are of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>i. e.</hi> though they may Lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet it is only thoſe that are <hi>Sincere</hi> that are the proper <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> or true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. So again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:96884:79"/>
Now to be without Guile here, is to be Sincere and without Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; whereby it appears, that a Man is Valued and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed in the Eyes of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Sincerity.</p>
            <p>And this ſometimes is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Name of Truth: <hi>I have no greater Joy,</hi> (ſays St. <hi>John, Ep.</hi> 3.4.) <hi>then to hear that my Children walk in Truth;</hi> that is, that they are Sincere Chriſtians. I am ſure it was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s great Comfort when he ſuppoſed himſelf near his Death, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>That in Sincerity and Godly Simplicity, he had his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in the World.</hi> He nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flattered himſelf, nor thoſe that heard him, but told them the plain Truth, ſhewing them both by what he himſelf, and they, muſt hope to go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: And this was the down-right Sincerity of his Heart,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:96884:80"/>
when he had no doublings, wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or turnings with God, but endeavoured as far as ever he could to pleaſe him, and do his Will. This alone has the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Heaven, and upon this the Bleſſed Land of Righteouſneſs, the Pleaſant Manſions of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality are Entailed. This is the Complement and Perfection of Holineſs, without which all our Religion is but a mere Shadow &amp; Pageantry. For then only is the Soul of Man ſaid to be Sincere, when it is fully and wholly carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out after that which is ſimply and abſolutely the beſt.</p>
            <p>And all Men that have any ſenſe of Religion, muſt own, that God and the Participation of his Nature, is abſolutely and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Compariſon the beſt thing in the World: And to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to a Union with God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied to be the greateſt
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:96884:80"/>
Happineſs the Mind of Man is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. And ſince this is not only ſimply the beſt, but the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt and compleat Felicity of our Nature, it follows that Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is then moſt perfect, when our Wills with all their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Deſires are fully and wholly carried out after it. Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wholly (I ſay) that is, without any By-ends, or Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, or Siniſter Reſpects of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Fame, or Gain, or any ſuch thing, but merely upon a clear Knowledg that it is the beſt thing in the whole Creation. For he whoſe Intention is not direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aright, can hardly attain that excellent Qualification our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſo much commended in his Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Now to the end we may judg of our own Sincerity, we may reſolve our ſelves by theſe Two plain Notes or Characters.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:96884:81"/>1. If our Religion be as well in Private as in Publick.</p>
            <p>For he that confines his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only to the Church, or to a Feſtival-Day, is like thoſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens that Chained up their gods, for fear they ſhould run away, and they ſhould never find them again. But when we are hearty in Religion, and it be deeply ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and impreſſed upon our Souls, it will exert and ſhew it ſelf, as well when none but God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as if Ten Thouſand Eyes of Men were upon it. For ſince we believe that God is Omnipreſent, and that the bright Eyes of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity are ever broad awake, and looking upon us, it argues little Fear and Veneration of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Being, if we can dare commit a Sin in his preſence, though no other Being in the World were privy to it. Therefore when all Circumſtances are fair and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:96884:81"/>
and concur to the Acting a pleaſant or profitable Vice with the greateſt Secrecy and Impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; then to Abſtain and Hate the Sin out of a Religious Fear of offending God, and debaſing our own Souls, it is a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the Purpoſes of our Hearts are Right and Sincere.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we adhere to God, and keep firm in the ways of Virtue, as well in Adverſity as Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie to be Religious when God incircles us with his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and Rains down Pearls as it were into our Mouths; but when he hides his Face, and writes bitter things againſt us, and a Storm of Miſeries and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions from without blows hard upon us, then to be Virtuous is truly Honourable and Praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. And as it si no great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:96884:82"/>
to practiſe a Virtue that is in Faſhion, or to Adorn our ſelves with a Modiſh Piety: But to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Virtue through rough and uneven Paths, and to be Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous when Holineſs is contemned and diſgraced; that ſhews a ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Reſolution, and that a Man Loves God becauſe he is the moſt Excellent Being.</p>
            <p>Theſe Notes and Characters of Sincerity are few and plain, and by them we may examine our own Hearts, and diſcern whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any Hypocriſie in them or not: And by theſe we may diſcover the ſtate of our Souls, without perplexing our ſelves with a Multitude of Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and Signs of our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which it may be upon an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act ſearch may prove either Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent or Unreaſonable. Nay certainly he that is throughly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with a Vigorous Senſe of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:96884:82"/>
God and Virtue, and makes it his whole buſineſs inceſſantly to breath after, though with the loſs and hazard of all theſe Worldly Enjoyments, yea even of Life it ſelf, ſhall find a more laſting Comfort, and a ſtronger Security for Heaven flowing from his own Soul, than if an Angel ſhould tell him he was Ordained to a Celeſtial Happineſs.</p>
            <p>And we have the more reaſon to endeavour after this Integrity and Uprightneſs of Heart, from its great Neceſſity and apparent Uſefulneſs. There are Two main Seaſons or Times of Tryal of a Chriſtian, wherein a Sincere and Candid Breaſt will be his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Strength and Support. And theſe are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Days of Affliction and Calamity. Proſperity is a very falſe Glaſs, and moſt commonly
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:96884:83"/>
repreſents us to our ſelves in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Colours and Features than really we are. But Adverſity and Affliction wipes off all this Painted Gloſs and Varniſh, and ſhews us the true Face of things. And in this Caſe, a Formal and Hypocritical Dreſs will do us no good. While we can draw Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at our own Ciſterns, we ſpeak well of God, and make a chearful Profeſſion of Religion: But when a ſevere Providence dries up the Well-ſprings of our Comforts, and leads us through a Scorching Wilderneſs, wherein we Combat with fierce and fiery-flying Serpents, then is the time of Tryal. And indeed the True and Native Glory of Virtue, is never made ſo Viſible and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, as when it is ſurround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and begirt with the greateſt Dangers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:96884:83"/>Adverſity is a proper mean to diſcover, whether our Love to God and Virtue be Sincere and Unfeigned, or whether it be Counterfeit and Adulterate. Which our Saviour intimated in a Parable in the Goſpel, where the Scorching Beams of the Sun, [<hi>i. e.</hi> the Times of Miſery and Tribulation,] quickly ſhew'd the difference of the Soil wherein that Divine Seed was caſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Hour of Death is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe Times which will diſcover our Sincerity. Men have not the ſame Apprehenſions of Sin in their Health and Strength, as when they are drawing near their End, and entring upon the borders of another World. For as the Body in Sickneſs Loaths even thoſe things that were moſt grateful and pleaſant in its Health: So is it with the Mind or Spirit:
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:96884:84"/>
When it foreſees that 'tis haſtning to another and ſtranger World, it diſtaſts and hates the thoughts of thoſe Sins it ſo freely Acted and Indulged it ſelf in before. For then the Body, which is the Root and Occaſion of Sin, being broken and out of order, the Soul may more freely and clearly behold the difference between Good and Evil, and accordingly is more ſenſibly affected with it. And the clearer ſight we have of Sin and Wickedneſs, the greater is that Horror and Fear the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience inflicts upon us, when we are ſenſible of our own Guilt. Now ſince the Hour of Death and Diſſolution of our Earthly Tabernacles makes ſo perfect a Repreſentation of Things to us, ſtript of all their outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, and diveſted of that Paint and Flouriſh we put upon them; it muſt needs be a mighty
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:96884:84"/>
ſupport and comfort to find the Face of our Souls Calm and Smooth, and our ſelves not bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with the Heavineſs and Weight of Guilt.</p>
            <p>But when the Sins of our paſt Days come into our Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and we conſider how Falſe we have been to God and our own Souls; when it may be we have betrayed our Faith and Religion to ſupport a frail and tottering Intereſt in this World; there will then be little elſe but a diſmal Scene of Horror pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to our Eyes. The near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Approach to that State wherein we muſt dwell for ever, ſtrikes a Chilneſs and Coldneſs to our very Hearts. And all becauſe we have loſt that Hope and Confidence which flows from Sincerity, when we have done our beſt to ſerve God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:96884:85"/>And if now I ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring into view this Frame and Temper of Spirit which we call <hi>Sincerity,</hi> Clothed with all its Native Richneſs and Glory, I ſhould ſooner want Words to expreſs it, than be able fully to repreſent the Excellency of it. Its Beauty is ſo faultleſs and irreprehenſible, and the ſweetneſs of its Nature ſo great, that there is nothing on Earth ſo Lovely and ſo Deſirable. 'Tis ſuch a State of Soul, which he that is poſſeſſed of, would not loſe; and he that has it not, (if he knew but the worth of it,) would give all the World, (if he had it in his power,) to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it. For certainly, if ever Virtue could be made Viſible to Mortal Eyes, it muſt be by this Excellent Frame and Temper of Mind which we term <hi>Sincerity.</hi> It hath all that Excellency and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:96884:85"/>
Worth that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of Wiſdom, which indeed is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Perfection of <hi>Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> It is better than Rubies, and all the things that are to be deſired, are not to be compared to it. The Fruit of it is better than Gold, and the Revenue than choice Silver. <hi>Whoſo</hi> finds Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, findeth Life, and ſhall obtain favour of the Lord. Which is enough one would think to render ſo Charming a Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion highly valuable in our Eyes; ſince there is nothing that is No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Good, but is ſome way or other contained in it.</p>
            <p>But if this be too general a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the Worth of it; take it more particularly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sincerity alleviates all Croſſes and Afflictions. Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Vexations, Miſeries, and Diſappointments make up a very
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:96884:86"/>
great part of Humane Life. The Son of God himſelf was not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from Humane Miſeries, but made his way unto Glory through Death and the Grave. And it is our Lot and Portion to arrive at our Bleſſedneſs through many Tribulations; neither muſt we forget that the Paſſage to the Celeſtial Paradiſe lies through a Valley of Tears. Therefore ſince we cannot hope to be perfectly freed from Calamities and Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Circumſtances in this Life, our next enquiry muſt be how to alleviate and make them tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And the moſt certain way for this, is to be Sincere, <hi>i. e.</hi> to have our Minds fully and wholly carried out after God and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>When a Man falls into Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity through his own Folly, or that a Great and Heinous Sin has been the immediate Cauſe of his
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:96884:86"/>
Affliction, he loſes his Peace and Quiet, becauſe his Conſcience tells him that thoſe things might have been avoided. But when Tribulations ariſe from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Heaven, and that a Man's Troubles are the effects of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs, and ſent as fit Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to make Tryal of his Patience, Reſignation and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; then the Mind is quiet, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive and compoſed, becauſe when it looks back, it hath no ugly and ſtaring Sins to affright it. From whence it evidently follows, that if we are immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fixed and grounded in the Sincere Love of God and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we cannot be hurt by any Affliction. Nay, the greateſt Miſery and Calamity will be eaſed, and the ſmart of it taken off, becauſe, while we are Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, our Hearts aſſure us of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Uſage, and a more Comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:96884:87"/>
State in another World. So that, let it be loſs of Friends, loſs of Liberty and Eſtate, or whatever elſe is accounted a Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in this Life, yet a Sincere Perſon knows that he is befriend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Holy and Kind Beings of the inviſible World; that a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Providence ſhrouds him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its Wings, and will hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter recompence this ſhort and light Affliction with a Great and Eternal Weight of Glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sincerity contains whatever is truly deſirable by the heart of Man. Are we pleaſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with a Beautiful Object? Can there be any thing more Beautiful and Lovely, than a Calm and Serene Soul, whoſe Glory and Luſtre is not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed and obſcured within, but it diffuſes and communicates ſuch Rays and Beams of Mild and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:96884:87"/>
Simplicity, even in the Eyes and outward Viſage, as muſt needs affect every Rational Being with Admiration and Love? Do Riches appear Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and Glorious? What Riches can be comparable to this ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Treaſure of Simplicity and Sincerity? And when the Mind is Adorned and Clothed with this, it is much more Bright and Dazeling than <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Glorious Apparel and Robes of Royalty. Beſides, Riches are fugitive and uncertain, whereas Sincerity is ſuch a Treaſure as can neither be taken from us, nor ever exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or drawn dry. Do the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this World affect our Hearts? We are to conſider then, that in the Judgment of all Wiſe Men, the Pleaſures of the Mind are much more Noble than thoſe of the Body: And Sincerity in this exceeds all
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:96884:88"/>
Earthly and Corporeal Pleaſures, in that it never burdens us with Satiety, nor torments us with the Fear of its Decay. Could we be delighted with Honour? Then know that the higheſt Honour in the World is to be like to God, who is the Greateſt Unity and Simplicity. Sincerity is a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thing, always ſteady, and one and the ſame for ever; but Hypocriſie and Diſſimulation is Changeable and Various, and goes always under a diſguiſe. In a Word, ſearch all that any way appears grateful and deſirable by the Heart of Man, and this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Qualification of Sincerity will be found to be much more Eligible. This Unites our Minds with God, and fits us to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Angelical Spirits, whoſe Natures are ſo much the more Excellent and Exalted, as they partake more of Uniformity and Simplicity.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:96884:88"/>3. The very Perfection of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs conſiſts in Sincerity. For certainly the moſt perfect State of Angels in the Regions of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiſts in this, that they love and ſerve God truly according to the utmoſt of their Powers. And this is what every Man may and ought to do. It is true, in this Life our Affections cannot be ſo vigorous and enlarged, nor our Deſires ſo comprehenſive as thoſe of an Angel; but they may be as Sincere and without Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. There is a great abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and allowance to be made to the Variety of Humane Imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillity and Imperfection. All Men are not born Philoſophers, and the very Notion of a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Being makes not the ſame lively and Impreſſion upon all, but he that retains ſuch a Senſe of it as keeps him ſteady and firm in the Practice of Virtue,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:96884:89"/>
ſhall never be forgotten by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs. Though all our Services are mean and poor, yet they may be hearty and unmixt; and we may expreſs a Cordial Senſe of our Love to God, though that Holy Fire do not flame and ſparkle with the Brightneſs of a Seraphim. Virtue and Goodneſs is not always to be meaſured by the higheſt Degrees, but by the Truth, Plainneſs and Simplicity of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Sincerity brings the trueſt Pleaſure in the World. For as all Corporeal Pleaſure conſiſts in the exerciſe of the Senſes, and is more or leſs according as it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects them: So when the Soul is Sincere, there ariſes in it a true ſenſe and taſt of Righteouſneſs, which brings an ineffable Pleaſure along with it. It muſt be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed indeed, that this lively and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:96884:89"/>
pleaſant ſenſe of Virtue, and that Gratefulneſs that ſprings from it, is a thing that is not to be made known by Words, but is only perceived by the inward ſenſe of the Soul it ſelf. And hence a Carnal and Animal Man may enjoy himſelf in Senſual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, while in the mean time he is a mere ſtranger to that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pleaſure that reſults from Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; becauſe that Principle which ſhould taſt the relliſh and ſweetneſs of it, is yet aſleep in him. Moreover all Earthly Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are muddy and defiled, and have a taſt of the Cask, that is, the Body wherein they Lodg: But the Pleaſures of Virtue are Refined, and run pure and clear for ever. Becauſe the Spring whence Virtuous Pleaſure derives, is Sincerity, which is a State and Condition pure and unmixed,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:96884:90"/>
without any Art or Adulterated Compoſitions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Sincerity begets a generous Boldneſs and Magnanimity. No Man can be more confident of the well-being of his Soul than the Sincere Perſon; and this Confidence makes him look Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and Dangers undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Face. The Sincere Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whoſe Conſcience can Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to him that he hath fathfully endeavoured to Serve and Obey God, is fully aſſured, (however it may fare with him here, yet) it ſhall go well with him in the other World. He knows that God will never be unkind to an Innocent or Penitent Perſon; and is aſſured that he can never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake what is his own Life and Nature, which ſurely an Unſelf-Intereſſsed and Univerſaliz'd Love is.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:96884:90"/>Wherefore ſuch a One, though it were in the Agonies of Death it ſelf, can chearfully commit himſelf into the Gracious Hands of God, and with an Humble Confidence truſt himſelf with the inviſible Guards of thoſe higher and better Regions. For what ſhall ſeparate us from the Love of God, ſaith St. <hi>Paul?</hi> Nothing ſurely, if our own Hearts do not Condemn us of Hypocriſie; for then we may reſt ſecure of God's Love, who always Loves for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: And his Love is Immutable and never changes, till we change by Inadvertencey and Folly.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, Sincerity fills the Soul with an Eternal Peace, and ſecures it from all Inteſtine Broils, Diſtractions and Tumults. It is this lower and troubled Air that
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:96884:91"/>
is ſubject to Thunder and Storms, while thoſe upper Regions above the Clouds enjoy a perpetual Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine and Calm. And it is Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and Diſſimulation, and a Guiltineſs and Conſciouſneſs that we have been Falſe to God and Virtue, that raiſes Storms and Troubles within our own Breaſts. But Sincerity ſets us above all theſe, and we Breath in a Freer and Purer Air, and our Souls are Calm and Compoſed, Fair and Lovely, as the Clear Face of Heaven. In this Soil grows the Tree of Life, and here are thoſe Rivers of Living Waters, which overflow and enrich the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God.</p>
            <p>In a Word, this State of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity is a more valuable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure than all the World. 'Tis every thing that a Man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, becauſe it makes him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of God who is an Infinite
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:96884:91"/>
Fulneſs of all Happineſs and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. After this State we ought earneſtly to contend, and never leave off our purſuit till we have attained to it. This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights the Heart of God and Man, and is ſo enraviſhing a Temper, that our Saviour could not but commend it in his Holy Apoſtle. Now that we may all preſs forward to this Mark, God of his Infinite Mercy grant, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Holy Spirit be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory now and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
